<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods holy house and service according to the primitive and most Christian forme thereof, described by Foulke Robarts, Batchelor of Divinity, and prebendary of Norvvich.</title>
            <author>Robartes, Foulke, 1580?-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121261</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856446</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856446</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10795)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1217:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods holy house and service according to the primitive and most Christian forme thereof, described by Foulke Robarts, Batchelor of Divinity, and prebendary of Norvvich.</title>
                  <author>Robartes, Foulke, 1580?-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 98, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Cotes [and Richard Hodgkinson], and are to be sold [by J. Crooke and R. Sergier] at the Grey-hound in Saint Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cotes printed *⁴ A-E⁴, Hodgkinson F-M⁴ (letter to ESTC from Katharine Pantzer).</note>
                  <note>Booksellers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Original N2 is cancelled by a bifolium printed by Cotes, the first leaf signed "N2" with an imprimatur on the verso including the words "intra decem menses proxima sequentes", the second with errata. The cancellandum N2, printed by Hodkinson and paginated 99-100, had the same text on the recto, and on the verso an imprimatur with "intra decem menses Septembris &amp; Ianuarii [sic]".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>L1 mutilated; p. 70 to end from Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church buildings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Posture in worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:21996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
GODS HOLY HOVSE AND SERVICE, According to the primitive and moſt Chriſtian forme thereof, deſcribed by <hi>Foulke Robarts,</hi> Batchelor of Divinity, and Prebendary of NORVVICH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 26. 8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have loved the habitation of thine houſe, and the place where thine honour dwelleth.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Cotes,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Grey-hound</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard. 1639.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:2"/>
            <head>To all ſuch, as through weakeneſſe of judgement, with ſome ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious feare, and not by any malevolent ſpirit of oppoſition and ſchiſme, are offended at the Decency of our Churches, and the Reverend demeanure of our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward expreſſions in Gods publique Worſhip.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Loving Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He worſhip of God hath of late yeares beene ſo carried in many places among us, as if therein men were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any buſineſſe relating unto God. The places of meetings being ſo ruinous and ſordid, the people in the act of prayers and praiſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning themſelves ſo, as if they ſate in counſell with God: (a geſture, of which <hi>Tertulian</hi> ſaith, that in prayer, it is <hi>irreligioſiſſimum,</hi> a moſt irreligious <note place="margin">L. de orat.</note> thing,) rather than devoute and humble worſhips. Much irreverence was in adminiſtring and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:21996:3"/>
the holy Communion. I have often conceived hereupon, that either Papiſt, Turke, or Pagan, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our faſhion, would thinke that either our Churches were not the houſes of the holy God, or that the people in them were not about Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Our preſent moſt reverend Metropolian hath in his Metropoliticall viſitation, layd thoſe grounds, which have already reformed much, and I truſt will (by Gods mercy) ſoone reduce all things in Gods worſhip, to due decency, and reverence, all England over; Not doubting of the like ſucceſſe in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which we finde in the Dioceſſe of <hi>Norwich:</hi> For while the right reverend Father now Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> for the time his Lordſhip was our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan (as an other <hi>Eliſhaeus,</hi> in the ſpirit of <hi>Elias)</hi> his Lordſhip ſo proceeded in this pious worke, as that <hi>the worke of the Lord proſpered in his hands.</hi> The houſe and ſervice of God ſhineth among us in the primitive ſplendor, to the great good liking of all ſober Chriſtians. But as when S. <hi>Paul</hi> preached of the reſurrection, <hi>Some beleeved, others mocked,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.</note> So upon ſight of this good worke, ſo happily begunne, and ſo effectually followed; ſome joyfully confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; others frowardly oppoſed. The one encouraged, the other exaſperated my poore zeale; firſt by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and private communications, &amp; now by prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this ſlender treatiſe, to put forth my ſelfe a weak labourer, under ſuch <hi>Aholiabs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bezaliels,</hi> maſter workemen.</p>
            <p>I doe not in all this little treatiſe frame any one propoſition, which I doe not in my conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb facs="tcp:21996:3"/>
to be the truth of God. Nor doe Iuſe any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument or reaſon, but ſuch as I apprehend naturally to inferre the concluſion. My deſire herein (God knoweth) is your ſatisfaction and right informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in that, which not a little concerneth Gods glory, and your good. Thinke not that I would reduce all Gods worſhip, to bodily geſtures; Neither imagine, that it belongeth to the ſoule alone: The ſoule is the moſt excellent part, whoſe intentions recommend the expreſsions of the body unto God. But the body is a part, and an eſſentiall part of the man; and muſt beare his part with the ſoule in Gods worſhip. If the body act alone, then doth God ſay, Man, where is thy ſoule? If the ſoule alone take all upon it; then ſaith God, where is, or what doth thy body? Where are thine eyes, thy hands, thy knees, thy legges, to declare and accompany the lifting up, the humility, and the confidence of thy ſoule? Thy whole man is to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in my worſhip: It is for God and for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that I do pleade thus earneſtly with my bretheren. How decent a thing is it in the eye of man, to behold bodies and ſoules accord and joyne together, in the holy worke? How doth the viſible and expreſsive devotion of one Chriſtian, beget and encreaſe the ſame in an other? And how powerfully ſhall the reverend behaviours and geſtures of an whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation together worke one upon an other? Is not God the more glorified when our devotion is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and advanced. O my bretheren; be not froward, but meeke and tractable. Boy ſtrous men, in a ſpirit of error or oppoſition or both, have made too much
<pb facs="tcp:21996:4"/>
ſtirre, troubled and affrighted honeſt hearts. On the other ſide, ſome men expreſsing devotion outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, give too much ſcandall through want of probity. But I beſeech you turne away your eyes from men; turne them upon God, and then turne them home upon your ſelves: And then, tell me; doe you not perceive the Majeſty of God to be ſo great, as that it becommeth the whole man, ſoule and body to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane himſelfe, in all points of humility and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, inward and outward, when he is in Gods ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſence? Is not the excellent goodneſſe of God ſuch, as drawes all mens eyes upon him, and feedes them all with expectation? Is not his bounty ſuch as filleth every living thing with plenty of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Shall not the eye then looke up towards God, in admiration and hope? Shall not the hand be lifted up, ſhewing the heart ready to receive the bleſsing, and to reach out thankes? Speake to God with the intention, judgement and fervency of the ſoule. Speake alſo by the expreſsions of the members of thy body. Speake by thy tongue; Speake by thine eyes; Speake by thine hands and by thy knees. The tongue interpreteth the meaning of the ſoule, by words. The eyes and hands interpret the confident expectation of the ſoule, by their elevation. The knees interpret the humilitie of the ſoule by bowing. And ſo the rest of our decent geſtures doe interpret the ſoule, every one in its owne language, which God intendeth, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth and accepteth; when they truly declare out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, what the ſoule conceiveth inwardly. But I am asked what neede theſe geſtures and poſtures
<pb facs="tcp:21996:4"/>
more now, than heretofore? Whereto I anſwer, that there is no more neede to uſe theſe decent and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend geſtures and expreſsions, in the worſhip of God now, than heretofore. And that if heretofore wee have been defective in what was requiſite, it is time that now we be reformed. Againe, if by heretofore, yee underſtand the ſpace of 40. or 50. yeares laſt paſſed: I confeſſe that what we performe now, may ſeeme a novelty. But if by heretofore you meane the beſt and primitive times, of the ages next the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and before the dayes ſuperſtition crept on: then I ſay that there is no more required now, than what was in uſe in the practiſe of Chriſtians hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. God therefore give us grace to diſcerne truth from error, and light from darkeneſſe, and not to bee put out of the way of true devotion, through a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nike feare of a ſuppoſed ſuperstition; heartily prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At my Study in Norwich,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March.</hi> 4. 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your loving brother, <hi>Fowlke Robarts.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:5"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Holineſſe.</item>
                  <item>2 Of the holy place.</item>
                  <item>3 Of the conſecration of Churches.</item>
                  <item>4 Conſecration of Churches is not Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but morall.</item>
                  <item>5 That conſecration belongeth alſo to our Churches under the Goſpell.</item>
                  <item>6 Names whereby, Churches, under the Goſpell, have beene called.</item>
                  <item>7 To aſcribe holineſſe unto Churches, to build them faire and to adorne them, is neither Popiſh, nor any way ſuperſtitious.</item>
                  <item>8 Gods ſervants are holy and not ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious.</item>
                  <item>9 Gods worſhip is to be performed with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward expreſsions.</item>
                  <item>10 The ſeverall geſtures uſed by Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, in his worſhip, are free from ſuperſtition</item>
                  <item>11 They who unjuſtly charge us with ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, are themſelves moſt ſuperſtitious.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21996:5"/>
            <head>GODS HOLY HOVSE AND SERVICE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I. <hi>Of Holineſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a twofold holineſſe: 1. Eſſentiall, Originall, and Primitive. 2. Accidentall and derivative.</p>
               <p>Eſſentiall, Originall, and Primitive holineſſe is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of God, or rather God himſelfe. <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy.</hi> Whom wee call Primitive and Originall holineſſe; becauſe that all other holineſſe is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from God. who is holy, in and of himſelfe, yea holineſſe it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21996:6"/>
Accidentall, derived or received holineſſe is that holineſſe which the Creature hath, who hath no holineſſe, but from God; as the Moone hath no light but from the Sunne.</p>
               <p>All the holineſſe of the Creature is accidentall. For the Creature may either have or want holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and yet ſtill remaine the ſame entire crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as the Devill is now in ſubſtance the ſame Creature, which he was before his fall, and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> after his converſion, the ſame perſon, which he was before<hi>:</hi> though his conditions be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p>Againe the holineſſe of the creature is either Inherent or Relative.</p>
               <p>Inherent holineſſe is that wherewith the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſo endued, as that it makes his very nature and diſpoſition holy, in voluntary conformity to the will of God; as in <hi>Lot,</hi> compared with the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and <hi>Michael,</hi> with the Devill.</p>
               <p>Of this holineſſe no creature is capable, under or beneath the reaſonable creature, which is man. For this holineſſe is a voluntary conſcious obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and conformity to Gods will: according to the words of Saint <hi>Aug. Affectu tenenda ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitas,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De diffin. Eccl. dogm.</note> the meaning whereof is, that holineſſe muſt be retained wittingly and willingly; and <hi>Origen</hi> telleth us, that <hi>qui verbo dei inſervit, in ſanctis ſe eſſe credat. i.</hi> He that conformeth himſelfe to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 42. <hi>in Levit.</hi>
                  </note> the Word of God, may aſſure himſelfe that hee is of the number of holy men; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth both theſe, when he ſaith, <hi>Yee have from the</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21996:6"/>
                  <hi>heart obeyed the forme of doctrine, which hath beene delivered unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Relative holineſſe is, when the Creature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any qualifying of his nature with inherent ſanctitie, is to be eſteemed holy, in relation to the holy uſe, whereto it is aſſigned. And in this ſence times, places, oyle, bread and ſeverall utenſills, <hi>Cum divino cultui applicantur. i.</hi> when they bee <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aq.</hi> 2 <hi>da.</hi> 2 <hi>de. q.</hi> 81. <hi>ar.</hi> 8.</note> applyed to divine worſhip are holy.</p>
               <p>Things are aſſigned to the worſhip of God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediately: as was the Tabernacle and the Temple, which are therefore holy, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 7. The time for Gods worſhip, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 11. Men made Prieſts, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. 41. Beaſts of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in ſacifice, of the words <hi>ſacrum facere:</hi> ſo the Oblation is a conſecration, <hi>Levit.</hi> 8. 28. And the Altar on which it is layd, is holy or ſanctified. <hi>Exod.</hi> 29. 44. Theſe and the like are therefore holy, becauſe they are for holy uſe, <hi>viz.</hi> for Gods worſhip, and that immediately, being of uſe in the very act thereof.</p>
               <p>Other things belong to Gods worſhip, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately: and therefore are holy in that ſence and degree<hi>:</hi> and of this ſort are thoſe things which concerne the maintenance of the Prieſts, as their Tithes, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27. 30. and thoſe fragments and ſhares of the Sacrifices alotted to be the Fee of the Prieſt, <hi>Levit.</hi> 2. 3. and the Citties with their ſuburbes, appointed for their habitation. All which though in regard of the Author of their conſecration, are by God himſelfe immediately
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21996:7"/>
made holy; yet in regard of their uſe, they are holy immediately, becauſe they are for the uſe of thoſe, who themſelves were uſed in the holy act of Gods Worſhip.</p>
               <p>But paſſing by all others of this kinde of holy things, I purpoſe to amplifie my ſelfe onely in the holy place, the houſe of God; or the place of Gods Worſhip, and the Service therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. II. <hi>Of the Holy Place.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know not why I ſhould not take it for granted, that there have beene from the beginning, certaine ſet places, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially deſigned for Gods Worſhip, howſoever we reade not of any houſes, temples, or ſuch like Fabriques, wherein to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, before the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Tabernacle by Gods direction: yet wee finde that there were Altars for this uſe, from the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> and we finde them fixed in their places, to the which devout forefathers repaired to Worſhip. And though <hi>Noahs</hi> Altar <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. be the firſt that we reade of, yet I make no doubt but that they had Altars before that time, even from the beginning. For we doe not finde, that any Altar ſet up either by <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 33. or by <hi>Iſaack Gen.</hi> 26. or by <hi>Abraham</hi> either <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21996:7"/>
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 13. or 12. Or that by <hi>Noah,</hi> were ſet up by any ſpeciall Commandement from God. And therefore it is very probable, that the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture taught them, that the place where God is to be Worſhipped, ought to be differenced from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places: and that what they offered unto God, ſhould be decently ſet forth and not either fluttiſhly or careleſly layd or throwne upon the bare ground, which nature teacheth to be too rude a faſhion, of offering a preſent and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the very heathen (who had no direction, but from the light of nature) had their Altars for their ſacrifices and Worſhip of their Gods. And when <hi>Iacob</hi> made his oblation <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. he powred his oyle, not upon the ground; but upon the toppe of the ſtone, which he had ſet up on end for that purpoſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>In the 35. of <hi>Gen.</hi> God doth give <hi>Iacob</hi> a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement concerning the building of an Altar at <hi>Bethel.</hi> But that doth not imply that <hi>Iacob</hi> knew not, by the light of nature, that oblations to God, ought to be layd on ſome pile, erected for that purpoſe, as appeareth by his former practiſe both at <hi>Bethel, Gen.</hi> 28. and at <hi>Shalem</hi> of <hi>Shechem</hi> to be his place of worſhip whileſt he lived there <hi>Gen.</hi> 33. And therefore in <hi>Gen.</hi> 35. God doth not ſo much informe <hi>Iacob,</hi> that there muſt bee a place for divine worſhip, ſpecially diſtinguiſhed, as put <hi>Iacob</hi> in minde of his promiſe which he had made <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. concerning his <hi>Bethel</hi> or place of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to be at <hi>Luz,</hi> according to his vow, and that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21996:8"/>
now ſpecially; when upon the ſcandall which his ſonnes had given in the land, the country was growne too hot for him<hi>:</hi> whereupon, as it was needefull for him to remove his dwelling from among the enraged <hi>Sichemites;</hi> ſo alſo to have ſuch a place for worſhip, where he might abide, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repayring to the Altar, which he had built at <hi>Shechem.</hi> And the commandes of God to <hi>Moſes</hi> concerning Altars to be made, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. relate not ſo much to the Altars themſelves, as the materials, whereof; the formes, wherein; and the uſes, for which, they ſhall be made. For it had long, or rather ever beene the uſe to have an Altar to ſpecifie the place of Gods worſhip, inſomuch as <hi>Abraham</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from <hi>Egypt,</hi> went to the place of the Altar which he had made at the firſt, and there he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the name of the Lord. And all this was long-before the Inſtitution of the Leviticall Prieſthood, and therefore before any Leviticall ceremony had any being, which ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, that neither an Altar, nor an oblation upon an Altar, nor the worſhip of God at an Altar, is any thing Levitical (though of uſe in the Leviticall worſhip) no more then many of our Churches are therefore Popiſh, becauſe that either they are now, or heretofore have beene uſed by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
               <p>Vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> God gave order to make a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, a building, or an houſe, whereat, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, he would be worſhipped. And ſuch a building
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21996:8"/>
it was, as ſorted with the condition of the people at that time<hi>:</hi> being rather a booth or tent, than an houſe. For as the people having then no ſetled abode, but being on their journey in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe had not then for their private harbour, any houſes faſtned and immove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble on their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<hi>:</hi> but tents or boothes, which might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up, carried along and pitched againe, as they ſhould be occaſioned<hi>:</hi> ſo alſo the Roome which they had for Gods worſhip was accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooveable and portable. Yea and after their ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Arke of God (though divers times removed from place to place) yet for a long time it remained in a tent, or under curtaines, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 2.</p>
               <p>This when holy <hi>David</hi> conſidered, he thought it unreaſonable, that he (though a King, yet a man) ſhould dwell in a better houſe, than any that God had for his owne worſhip: and thereupon reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to provide God of a more magnificent habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or place of worſhip; but God would not have it of <hi>Davids</hi> building, who had beene <hi>a man</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Chro. 28. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>of warre, and ſhed much blood: Salomon</hi> therefore choſen thereto by God, undertooke and finiſhed the worke, which continuing in glory the ſpace of 400. yeares, to the 19. of the Raigne of King <hi>Nabuchadnozor,</hi> was burnt downe by the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeans,</hi> who alſo carryed away the people of <hi>Iudah</hi> Captives to <hi>Babylon,</hi> where when they had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the ſpace of 70. yeares, they returned home, and builded a ſecond houſe for Gods worſhip
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21996:9"/>
which with ſome magnificent alterations in the time of <hi>Herod</hi> the great, continued: the ſpace of 490. yeares, unto the 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. yeare of the incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our bleſſed Saviour.</p>
               <p>After the aſſention of our Saviour into heaven (the Apoſtles and Diſciples being diſperſed on broad, and thereby the Goſpell Preached over the world) men were begotten to the Church ſaith; and aſſembled themſelves as they might in <note place="margin">See <hi>Mead</hi> Churches.</note> private houſes, in woods, in dennes, and caves: yet ſo as, their meeting places were certaine and ſet a part from common uſe to the worſhip of God and Church edification: and though the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the heathen was great, raiſing frequent and cruell perſecutions againſt the Churches: yet they beganne betimes to builde Churches and as their number and meanes increaſed to enlarge, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne them: inſomuch as in this Iſland <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathca,</hi> having here preached the Goſpell, builded a Church in the Iſle of <hi>Avalon</hi> or <hi>Aveland</hi> in <hi>Somerſet-ſhire,</hi> which afterwards, <hi>Devi</hi> Biſhop of Saint <hi>Davids</hi> repaired<hi>:</hi> and laſtly King <hi>Ivor.</hi> Converted to a Monaſtery.</p>
               <p>Neither onely in this Iſland, but alſo all over the world, Churches became by degrees to bee builded, enlarged and adorned. And though of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the fury of perſecutors demoliſhed them<hi>:</hi> yet ſtill as the Churches obtained any peace and favour, they repaired, enlarged and beautified their Churches<hi>:</hi> In which (as alſo in their former leſſe conſpicuous and ſumptuous places of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21996:9"/>
meetings) they might neither buy nor ſell, nor treate of worldly matters, nor eate and drinke, other than at holy Communions. So were the <note place="margin">Tert. Apol.</note> places of an holy eſteeme <hi>Holy Places.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. III. <hi>Of Conſecration of Churches.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Either are Churches therefore holy one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe they are applyed to holy uſes: but they are firſt made holy, by ſpeciall dedication and conſecration, of which the learned <hi>Zanchius</hi> giveth this definition: <hi>Conſecratio est, praemiſsis precibus cum gratiarum actione, templa ad</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> 4 <hi>precep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. c.</hi> 19. <hi>q.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſolum divini cultus uſum deputare, ordinare que ac benedicere; &amp; incipere jam uſurpare, i.</hi> Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is with prayers and thankeſgivings to depute and to ordaine, and bleſſe Temples, to the onely uſe of the worſhip of God; and accordingly to begin to put them in ure.</p>
               <p>In which words we may conſider three things. 1. The Alienation. 2. The Aſſignation. 3. The Solemnity of the Act.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Alienation is when the ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Church is built, together with the Church or building it ſelfe, and ſo much ground about it as is intended for the Churchyard, being all yet but common ground and building; <hi>i.</hi> ſuch as the owner may retaine in his owne hands and convert
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21996:10"/>
to what uſe he will, either publicke or private, is ſurrendred into the hands of the Biſhop, to the end that it may be made holy unto God, whereby the right which the owner had therein, is quite determined; and the common uſe whereto it might have beene put, is for ever prevented and put by. As, when King <hi>David</hi> intended to build an Altar unto God, in the threſhing floore of <hi>Araunah,</hi> he firſt buyeth it out of the right and poſſeſſion of <hi>Araunah,</hi> that when the Altar is there built, hee may conſecrate it unto God, and <hi>Araunah</hi> for ever be excluded, and debarred from any claime thereto.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Aſſignation is the inveſting of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, in the right and poſſeſſion of that ground and building<hi>:</hi> For when the owner hath ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it into the hands of the Biſhop, and given livery and ſeizin thereof to the Biſhop, ſo as now the Biſhop is thereof fully poſſeſſed; yet is the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop herein but Gods Atturny, ſo ſeized and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of this ground and building to Gods uſe; to the which he doth by ſpeciall ceremony and ſolemnity aſſigne it. Whereupon it becommeth now the houſe and ground of God, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is thereof ſpecially poſſeſſed. In the Old Teſtament we finde, that God, upon the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Dedication, doth viſibly ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in poſſeſſion; for when <hi>Moſes</hi> (who <hi>Exod.</hi> 40. is commanded to <hi>Annoint and hallow the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and all that is therein)</hi> had verſe 23. <hi>finiſhed the whole worke, i.</hi> done all in manner and forme, as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21996:10"/>
he had beene directed, then <hi>v.</hi> 34. <hi>A Cloud covered the tent of the Congregation, and the glory of the Lord filled the Tabernacle.</hi> So alſo 1. <hi>King</hi> 8. when the Temple being finiſhed, all things had beene ſet in their order therein, and bountifull Sacrifices offered <hi>verſe</hi> 5. and that the Prieſts were come out of the holy place, <hi>verſe</hi> 10. The place being now reſigned and prepared for God, to take his poſſeſſion<hi>:</hi> then <hi>the Cloud filled the houſe of the Lord,</hi> verſe 10. <hi>And the glory of the Lord filled the houſe of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Solemnitie did alſo ever accompany this worke; <hi>Iacob</hi> erecting his Altar, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the place to be none other than the houſe of God, a dreadfull place, ſetteth up the ſtone on end, powreth oyle thereon for an obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, maketh there his vowes to God, which hee afterwards performed <hi>cap.</hi> 35. Who will, may reade at large, with what ſolemnity the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle was dedicated, <hi>Exod.</hi> 40. And the Temple of <hi>Salomon</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8. And the ſecond Temple, 1. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 6. And when <hi>Iudas Macchabeus</hi> had renewed the Altar, which together with the Temple, the heathen had prophaned<hi>:</hi> what time the heathen had prophaned it, even in that was it dedicated, with Songs and Cytterns and Harpes and Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls. And then all the people fell on their faces, worſhiping and prayſing the God of heaven: who had given them ſo good ſucceſſe: and ſo they kept the Dedication of the Altar 8. dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21996:11"/>
               <head>CAP. IIII. <hi>Conſecration of Temples and Churches, is not Leviticall but Morall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a conceite taken up upon ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and propagated by tradition, without ground, that conſecrations were meere Leviticall rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, againſt which fancie; we reaſon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating of places to Gods Worſhip, being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther peculiar to the Iewes, under the Prieſt-hood of <hi>Levi,</hi> nor any type of any thing to bee fulfilled in Chriſt, are not Leviticall but morall: whereto the very heathen have beene directed, by the light of nature <note n="a" place="margin">See <hi>Liv. hist. Ro. dec.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 9. <hi>Tacit. hiſt. l.</hi> 4 <hi>fl. Vopiſ. in vita Aureli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani.</hi>
                  </note> in all times among all nations. Nature informeth us, that there is a God; that God muſt be Worſhipped, that there muſt be places, where publickely to performe that worſhip; heathen men know all this and practiſe accordingly. And will any man ſay or imagine, that to give thankes to God for affording a place for his publicke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: or by prayers to begge of God, that the prayers there made, the Word there Preached, and the Sacraments there received, may be all effectuall under Gods bleſſing, is a matter Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. Or it is a Iewiſh thing to ſeperate the place of Gods worſhip from common uſe? Or to ſhut
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21996:11"/>
up the houſe of God from being an houſe of Merchandiſe? Where lyeth either Iudaiſme, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition or any errour in all this? And this is all that which wee call conſecration or dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Doth not Nature teach men to acknowledge God, to be the Author of all the good things which we receive, and therefore to receive them with thankes for them, and prayers to God for his bleſſing upon them to our uſe; for every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 5.</note> of God is good if it be received with thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, for then it is ſanctified by the Word and Prayer: In regard whereof, God taught us not <note place="margin">Deut. 20. 5.</note> to enter upon the poſſeſſion of a private houſe, without ſo dedicating it. Shall conſecration hold generally in the uſe of all Gods bleſſings, even of thoſe which concerne onely the uſe of this life? and is the creature ſanctified to our uſe, when it is received with prayer and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving? and ſhall wee be affrayd to ſay that the Church is ſpecially ſanctified to our uſe, or to call it a conſecrated or holy place, when it is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, ſet a part for the worſhip of God, for the benefit of the ſoule, and for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the whole man, to everlaſting Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
               <p>We muſt not call every thing Iewiſh or Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, which is done by a Iew or Levite: no more than we terme every thing Popiſh which is done by a Papiſt. But as that onely is Popiſh which is peculiar to a Papiſt, and wherein he in doctrine or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21996:12"/>
ceremonie innovateth againſt the Word of God, and the faith and practiſe of the primitive and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Church; ſo that is Iewiſh or Leviticall, which is peculiar to the people of the Iewes or Leviticall worſhip; but that which becommeth all men to doe, in all times and places, and whereto they are guided by the light of nature, the Word of God, and preſidents of Antient Orthodox Fathers, and ſincere primitive Chriſtians, is neither Iewiſh, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticall, nor Popiſh; but morall pious and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
               <p>That exemplary Knight, not unworthily ſtiled <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Hen Spelm.</hi>
                  </note> a Magazine of learning, doth in his booke <hi>de non temerandis eccleſiis,</hi> extract the morall from what was Leviticall in the Worſhip of God, from the firſt inſtitution of the Order of <hi>Levi,</hi> unto the period or expiring thereof, by taking into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the diſtinct regions (as I may call them) of the Temple. In the firſt whereof being the <hi>holy of holyes,</hi> was the divine preſence in the Arke, the Oracle and Mercie ſeate; into which none but the high Prieſt might enter, and that but once in the yeare, and not without blood. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, being the holy place, which was the court of the Prieſts, was the Ceremoniall worſhip and attonement by ſacrifices, oblations and other Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticall rites; and therefore here were the holy veſſels, the Shew-bread, the incenſe Altar; and in the Court the Altar of burnt Sacrifice. The third was the outward Court, or Court of the people, called <hi>Salomons</hi> Porch: and this place
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21996:12"/>
was for thankeſgiving, Prayer, and Preaching. The two firſt regions or places of the Temple, were Ceremoniall in wordly elements: Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, ſignifying ſome Spirituall things, to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in Chriſt. Secrete for the things there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, were remote from the eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Leviticall, adminiſtred onely by that tribe. Iudaicall, for the uſe onely of that people (tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, to endure onely to the time of reformation. But the third place, with the duties there perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, was free from the Ceremonies of the two former, all open to the people. The myſteries were there explained; all the Tribes, people, and nations had their acceſſe thither. The duties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in this region, and ſo the place it ſelfe, were and are to continue to the end of the world <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> though not in <hi>individuo, i.</hi> in the ſame kinde, though not in the ſame particular, to be of the ſame uſe al the world over; for ſo ſaith Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, <hi>Mine houſe ſhall be called an houſe of Prayer</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſ.</hi> 56. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>to all nations.</hi> And the ſayd worthy Knight fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſerveth, that our Saviour Chriſt reformed not any thing in the two former places, the functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there being at an end; but for ſo much as the functions of the third were to continue, therefore he purgeth that place, and reſtoreth it to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and due ſanctity.</p>
               <p>An Argument drawne from the Tabernacle or Temple to our Churches, in things Morall, and founded on the Law of nature is good, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth ſtrongly. For though the vayle of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21996:13"/>
Temple be rent downe, from the toppe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome; and an end be put to the Typicall and Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Worſhip: Yet the Temple was not then throwne downe, but continued ſtanding, the ſpace of 40. yeares after the aſcention of our Saviour into heaven, for Morall worſhip and Service, and was accordingly uſed by Chriſtian people, for prayer and preaching, as is evident <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 1. and <hi>cap.</hi> 5. 20, 21. And no doubt but that to this day it might have continued the houſe of God, for morall worſhip<hi>:</hi> if the impietie of the Iewes had not provoked God to bring the <hi>Romans</hi> upon them, to deſtroy both them and their Temple. The neceſſitie that lay upon the Temple to bee throwne downe, in regard of the Prophecie of our Saviour Chriſt, foretelling the ruine thereof, proceeded from our Saviour his foreknowledge, looking to the vengeance which the people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for their ſinnes, and not from the nature of the Temple, which might have continued for morall worſhip, though the Leviticall be ceaſed. And to that effect the Maſters of the Centuries (well knowne to be no friends to ſuperſtition) obſerved well in theſe words; <hi>The Chriſtians are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>dayly in the Temple with one accord: Act.</hi> 2. <hi>The Apoſtles ceaſed not dayly, there to teach and to Preah Chriſt. Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Peter and Iohn went up to the Temple to pray, and they did Preach to the People, when they flocked together in Salomons Porch, Act.</hi> 3. <hi>And the Apoſtles, being delivered out of priſon, are commanded not to Preach the Goſpell in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21996:13"/>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>And the whole congregation came toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with one accord in Salomons Porch,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo is apprehended in the Temple; and all this was after that our bleſſed Saviour had by his death and reſurrection put an end to all Leviticall cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
               <p>If any object here, that when the <hi>Romans</hi> had burnt downe and deſtroyed the Temple, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God was ſo great againſt it, as not to ſuffer any rebuilding of it any more: the anſwere is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>viz.</hi> that the anger of God was not againſt the being of an houſe, for his worſhip in that place<hi>:</hi> but becauſe the unbeleeving <hi>Iewes</hi> (as they did hate Chriſt, ſo being animated by that grand enemie of Chriſt, the Apoſtate <hi>Iulian)</hi> endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to erect there a Temple for Leviticall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ceremonies, to be ſet up againe, in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and ſlander to the Croſſe of Chriſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Goſpell. For the Chriſtians did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward in that very place, where the Temple ſtood, and where the <hi>Iewes</hi> were not permitted by God to rebuild, ſet up a very faire and goodly Church, for Chriſtian worſhip, which Church was long bleſſed of God and became a Patriarchall ſeate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21996:14"/>
               <head>CAP. V. <hi>That Conſecration belongeth alſo to our Churches un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Churches under the Goſpell, are in the ſame condition with the third regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Temple, among the <hi>Iewes: viz. Gods houſe of prayer, to all nations.</hi> And therefore as that was ſo ours muſt be, no <hi>houſe of Merchandize:</hi> but ſet a part from all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, for the worſhip of God, thankeſgiving, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Novel.</hi> 6.</note> prayer, preaching, and the like acts and exerciſes of Religion. <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> made a Law, that eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall perſons ſhould not celebrate divine offices, in places not conſecrate. And ſo hath the Church anciently accuſtomed, to make the places of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious meetings, peculiar and proper for onely religion and devotion, by the ſolemne rites of conſecration.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> preaching 1200. yeares ſince, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. de temp.</hi> 256.</note> at the conſecration of a Church, beginneth thus; <hi>Celebritas hujus congregationis dedicatio eſt domus orationis. i.</hi> The ſolemnity of this meeting is the dedication of the houſe of prayer. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 5.</note> telleth us that he and <hi>Felix</hi> had beene invited <hi>ad conſecrationem baſilicae per Baſsianum. i.</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of a Church by <hi>Baſsianus. Athanaſius</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ep. ad Conſt.</note> doth divers times mention the conſecration of Churches. Before all theſe <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <note place="margin">Apol. ad Const.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexandria</hi> (as teſtifieth <hi>Athanaſius)</hi> conſecrated
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21996:14"/>
a Church with great ſolemnity. <hi>Euſebius</hi> relateth that upon the death of the tyrant <hi>Maximianus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Optatum exhibetur ſpectaculum Celebrationes, viz. eccaeniorum per Civitates &amp; Oratoriorum recens ſtructorum conſecrationes. i.</hi> There appeareth a very joyfull ſpectacle or ſight, <hi>viz.</hi> the yearely comemorations of the Dedications of Churches, and Conſecrations of others newly ſet up. And howſoever Pope <hi>Higinus</hi> about the yeare 140. <note place="margin">Decr. de conſec. dist. i. e. omnes Baſilicae.</note> made a Decree that Churches ſhould be conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; yet it is plaine that that Decree was but the ratification of what was then in uſe, rather than any innovation or bringing in of a new faſhion. For there were Conſecrations of Churches under Pope <hi>Evaristus</hi> about 40. yeares before that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree <note place="margin">Gratia.</note> of <hi>Higinus:</hi> and that either ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or preſently after, the death of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Evangeliſt; for I finde ſome uncertainety here, in matter of Chronologie, though the ſpace of the time in difference is not long. And indeede how can we imagine otherwiſe, but that ſo ſoone as the Chriſtians had any certaine places for their religious meetings, they did for the more Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table expectation of Gods bleſſing in them, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them unto God by prayer and thankeſgiving?</p>
               <p>Yea and the Primitive Chriſtians were wont at the dedication of their Churches to bee excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly affected, and taken with exceſſive joy, at theſe Dedications: whileſt they conſidered that God had, as it were taken an houſe among them, therein to entertaine, feede, feaſt, and cloath them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21996:15"/>
with his owne ſpeciall preſence, his holy Word, the bleſſed Sacraments, and the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, where alſo they might Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and impart themſelves by their prayers unto God<hi>:</hi> and confidently begge and have for all their neceſſities and occaſions, ſufficiency of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe<hi>:</hi> and therefore as in the Old Teſtament we finde, that when <hi>Salomon</hi> Dedicated the Temple, he held a great feaſt, the ſpace of 14. dayes, <hi>And</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>then he bleſſed the people, and the people bleſſed him, and went to their tents joyfull and glad of heart, for all the goodneſſe which the Lord had done for David his ſervant, and for Iſrael his people:</hi> and as in the 6. Chapter of the booke of <hi>Ezra, They kept the Dedication of the houſe of God with joy, &amp;c.</hi> So alſo the primitive Chriſtians uſed with much gladneſſe and rejoycing to ſolemnize the Dedications of their Churches. <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the place laſt cited addeth theſe words, <hi>Hic Pſalmodiis ac reliquis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>nobis traditis elogiis: Illic divinis ac mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis mysteriis, &amp;c. eccleſiarum preſides panegyricis. conventus ornabant;</hi> and then, <hi>totis animi viribs hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larique mente precando &amp; gratias agendo deum bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum authorem venerabantur. i.</hi> Here with Hymnes and divine prayſes. There with ſacred and deepe Miſteries, &amp;c. yea and the governors of the Churches did with publicke ſpeeches ſolemnize the meetings; and with ſongs and prayſes from the bottome of their hearts, and with cheerefull mindes, prayſing and giving thankes, they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God the Author of all their good. Saint
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21996:15"/>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> at the like ſolemnity hath theſe words, <hi>Conſecrationem altaris hodie Celebramus (fratres) &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm.</hi> 255.</note> 
                  <hi>cuſtè ac merito celebramus feſtivitatem, in qua unctus eſſe lapis, in quo nobis divina Sacrificia conſecran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. i.</hi> We this day (brethren) celebrate the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of the Altar, and good cauſe have we to Celebrate that feſtivity, wherein that ſtone hath beene anoynted, upon which the Divine ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are conſecrated for us.</p>
               <p>And yet further, as when <hi>Macchabaeus</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled or new dedicated the Sanctuary of God, and new built the Altar of burnt offerings, which the heathen had prophaned; they doe not onely Celebrate that Dedication, with great joy at that time: but alſo ordaine an anniverſary or yearely commemoration and continuation thereof, to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity: So alſo the primitive Chriſtians, when they had once conſecrated a Church, did uſe ever after to keepe a ſolemne yearely feaſt, upon the conſecration day, for a thankefull memoriall of that bleſſing, as may appeare by the title of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Sermons of Saint <hi>Augustines, In anniverſario</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom.</hi> 10. <hi>de temp.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>dedicationis Templi vel Altaris. i.</hi> In the yearely ſolemnity of the Dedication of the Temple or Altar. In one of which Sermons, hee ſpeaketh thus<hi>: Quotieſcunque (fratres Chriſsimi) alt aris</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm.</hi> 252.</note> 
                  <hi>vel templi festivitatem colimus, ſi diligenter ac fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter attendimus &amp; ſancte ac juſte vivimus, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid in Templis manufactis agitur, id totum in nobis ſpirituali aedificatione completur. i.</hi> as often as (moſt deare brethren) we keepe the Feaſt day of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21996:16"/>
Temple or Altar, if we diligently and faithfully heede it; and live uprightly and godlily, then whatſoever is done in the Temples made with hands, that is all fulfilled in us by ſpirituall edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had built that faire <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom. l</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25. <hi>Niceph. hiſt. ed. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 50.</note> and famous Temple in Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> as he drew thither all the Biſhops from the Councell of <hi>Tyre,</hi> for the conſecration thereof<hi>:</hi> So from that time the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> did yearely, for the ſpace of eight dayes together, celebrate the commemoration or remembrance of that Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſaith <hi>de eccaenijs celebrandis,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Naz. orat. in nav. domicum. orat.</hi> 43.</note> 
                  <hi>legem veterem eſſe, eamque perclare conſtitutam. i.</hi> That the Law for the yearely commemorations of the Dedications of Churches, is both ancient and worthily enacted.</p>
               <p>And to this day, as in other parts of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, ſo in this Realme and Kingdome, we doe celebrate theſe commemorations in divers Pariſhes (though men know not, that the Wake-day-feaſts (as we call them) which they yeerely keepe, are the dayes of the conſecration of their Churches, in thoſe Pariſhes, and therefore ſhould be celebrated with more ſeriouſneſſe, reverence and devotion then uſually they doe.</p>
               <p>About the one and thirtieth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> 8. Holy dayes were growne to ſuch an unreaſonable number, as that men had almoſt no time, to worke and intend the buſineſſe of their callings; ſervants had ſo many play dayes, and poore people ſo few working dayes, as began to breed much inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21996:16"/>
by reaſon of ſo much idleneſſe. Wherefore there came forth injunctions from the King by the Convocation, for the reſtraint thereof<hi>:</hi> and whereas every Pariſh generally had two ſpeciall and peculiar holy dayes of their owne every yeare; the one to the memoriall of the Saint, by whoſe name the Church was called (whom they of the blinder times, ſuperſtitiouſly adoring, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Patron of the place) The other was in commemoration of the dedication of the Church: it is injoyned that the Feaſt of the Saint or Patron be no longer obſerved as an holy day, but that it ſhall be lawfull to all and ſingular perſons to goe to their worke, myſtery or occupation, upon the ſame day, except the ſayd feaſt be ſuch, as elſe muſt be univerſally kept, as an holy day. But the Feaſt of the Dedication of the Church, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction will have it ſtill to be continued, though yet ſo, as it muſt not be celebrated upon any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king day; but in all places alwayes on the firſt Sunday in <hi>October:</hi> but we finde that in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, both theſe feſtivals are let downe, and ſo farre diſcontinued, as that there is no remembrance of them left, though yet in many places in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, there is a plaine continuation of the one of them, or rather of them both contracted into one. For where the Wakes in <hi>England</hi> are yet in uſe, I conceive that they continue a remainder of the <hi>eccaenia,</hi> or Dedication Feaſts<hi>:</hi> Firſt, for that thoſe feſtivals are of ſo great antiquity, and therefore the liker, for the reverence thereof to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21996:17"/>
Secondly, for that they were wont to bee celebrated with ſo great ſolemnity as kept them the rather from being forgotten; and by ancient Councells were placed in the ſame ranke with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Mogunt. de ſeſt. an. ca.</hi> 36. <hi>Concil. Lugdun. de conſecr. diſt.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Easter</hi> day, <hi>Aſcention</hi> day, and <hi>Whitſon</hi> day, and other ſuch great and eminent feſtivals. In a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell held at <hi>Oxford, Anno.</hi> 1222. the Feſtivalls are diſtributed into three rankes, and the Feaſt of the Dedication of a Church is numbred with thoſe which are <hi>omni veneratione obſervanda. i.</hi> To be kept with all ſolemnity and devotion. And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeeing that when the other, <hi>viz.</hi> the Feaſt day of the Saint was diſſanulled, this of the Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ratified. All which being layd together, doe make it very probable that the Wake day Feaſt is of the two the continuation of the Dedication Feaſt (for one of them (if not a conjunction of both) it is certainely) and yet not without ſome reference to the day of the Saint.</p>
               <p>For if men (where theſe Feaſts are yet in uſe) looke well into it, they ſhall plainely finde, that the dayes whereon they keepe theſe Wakes, are the dayes of the memoriall of thoſe Saints, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, by whoſe names the ſeverall Churches are called. I can inſiſt in many; and the <hi>Britiſh</hi> word, whereby the <hi>Britaines</hi> doe call thoſe ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities <note place="margin">Gwul-Mab-Sant. <hi>i.</hi> The Saints holy day.</note> or feſtivals, doth import as much. For though the Churches were built, and houſes unto God, for his Worſhip; yet to diſtinguiſh one from another, they have every one the name of ſome Saint, whoſe memory the Biſhop, Founders, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21996:17"/>
people then thought good to continue. So that each of our Churches is the houſe of God, and the memoriall of ſome Saint, according to the words of Saint <hi>Augustine, Nos martyribus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stris</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Civit. dei. l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>non templa ſicut diis, ſed memorias, ſicut homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus mortuis (quorum apud deum vivunt ſpiritus) fabricamus. i.</hi> We build not any Temples to our Martyrs, as if they were Gods; but memorialls as of dead men (whoſe ſoules are alive with God) and yet they reputed thoſe Churches or ſo called them, <hi>Aedes Sacras,</hi> holy or Sacred houſes. For, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. de vit. conſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> they are ſet a part from common uſe; they are aſſigned to Gods Worſhip, they are conſecrated with ſolemne and ſpeciall rites, and given up into Gods poſſeſſion, and their Dedications have long beene commemorated with yearely ſolemnites; whereupon it was decreed in the Councell of <hi>Gangra. Si quis docet domum Dei Contemp ibilem eſſe vel congregationes quae in ea fiant, Anathema</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>fit. i.</hi> If any man teach that the houſe of God or the Congregations there aſſembled, are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned or ſlighted, let him be accurſed. And further the words in that Councell are, <hi>Domos</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Dei honoramus, &amp; conventus qui in iis fiunt, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſanctos &amp; utiles ſuſcipimus, non claudentes pietatem in domibus, ſed omnem locum in Dei nomine aedificatum honoramus. i.</hi> Wee doe honour the houſes of God, and embrace the aſſemblies there, as holy and good. Not that we ſhut up Pietie in houſes, but that wee honour all places which are built to the name of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21996:18"/>
So then the Pietie of thoſe times reputed Churches holy places, and yet no otherwiſe holy than by a Relative holineſſe. <hi>viz.</hi> in regard of their conſecration, and the uſe whereto they are thereby aſſigned, which yet giveth no man liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ever the more to ſlight the Church: For though creatures beneath the reaſonable, be capable of no other holineſſe, than this Relative holineſſe, yet have they ſoundly ſmarted, who have dared to prophane ſuch holy things, <hi>Nabuchadonoſor</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 25.</note> burnt up the houſes of the Lord, and the Pillars of the baſeſſe, and the brazen Sea did the <hi>Caldaeans</hi> breake in peeces, &amp;c. But then marke what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; it is not long before that <hi>Nabuchadonoſor</hi> is called to his account for all this; when his Kingdome is departed from him, and he driven <note place="margin">Dan. 4.</note> from men doth eate graſſe as Oxen, hath his body wet with the dew of heaven, his haire grow like Eagles feathers, and his nailes like the birds ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons. <hi>Baltaſar</hi> will needes prophane the holy veſſels, and command them from the houſe of <note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> God, for himſelfe to carouſe in, among his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines; But the wrath of God doth quickely powre him out a Cup of vengeance, and ſad newes; that night he loſt his life, and the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> poſſeſſed his Kingdome, <hi>Antiochus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Mac. 1.</note> maketh the like havocke in the Temple, and the holy things thereof as <hi>Nabuchadonoſor</hi> had done before: and not long after he is met withall by the hand of God, which ſmote him with an invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and incureable plague, tormenting his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21996:18"/>
bowels and inward parts, his fleſh rotting, his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe ſwarming with Lice, and ſtinking ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly, as not to be endured; and in this wretched caſe, he dyed miſerably on the wilde Mountaines. And one maine motive ſtirring God to expoſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> to the fury of the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> was, for that <note place="margin">2 Chro. 36. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>they polluted the houſe of the Lord, which he had hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth not the fearefull death of <hi>Vzzah</hi> tell us, how wary we muſt be, and what heede we muſt take of medling with things hallowed or Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated; for what did he but onely touch the Arke with his hand, in no contempt or evill meaning but with a good reſpect, to keepe it from falling? But the Arke was holy, and <hi>Vzza</hi> his hand was not to meddle therewith; he therefore dyed for this preſumption; and yet the holineſſe of the Arke was but relative holineſſe.</p>
               <p>What ſhould I ſay of the Sabboth day among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> or of the Lords day among the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? was the one? Or is the other holy, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by a relative holineſſe? And yet wee know, how ſeverely they have beene puniſhed, which violated the holineſſe of the Sabboth in the Old Teſtament: and we have knowne of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny terrible judgements, which have overtaken ſuch as have abuſed the other. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is the holy Citty, and heaven it ſelfe is an holy place; yet no otherwiſe holy than in relation to God there ſpecially preſent. If then heaven be holy, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> holy, the Lords day holy, the Sabboth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21996:19"/>
was holy; then the Church or place conſecrated for Chriſtians to aſſemble in, for the publicke worſhip of Almighty God, is therefore holy, becauſe being ſo conſecrated, it hath ſuch relation to God and his worſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. VI. <hi>Names whereby Churches under the Goſpell have beene called.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur <hi>Engliſh</hi> word Church, which in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is ſounded Kyrke, commeth of the Greeke word Κυριακὴ, of the word Κύριοσ, a Lord, ſo Κυριακὴ or Church is, as if you ſhould ſay, belonging to the Lord; anſwerable whereto is the Latine name <hi>Dominicum,</hi> by which the Church was anciently called, of the word <hi>Dominus</hi> a Lord, ſo wee have it, <hi>Ruffin. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Sequere me ad Dominicum, i.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De verbis domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nii Ser.</hi> 15.</note> Follow me to the Church, Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us the reaſon, why the Church is ſo called. <hi>Quemadmodum tempus Deo ſacrum, dicitur dies Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicus: Ita locus Deo dicatus, dicitur Dominicum, i.</hi> As the time which is holy unto God is called the Lords day, ſo the place which is dedicated unto God, is called <hi>Dominicum, i.</hi> The Lords houſe. And thus the Church in the new Teſtament, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth in phraſe with our forefathers in the Old Teſtament, who uſually call the Temple and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21996:19"/>
places of Gods Worſhip, the houſe of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Places of Chriſtian and Religious meetings <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> have had the names of <hi>Cryptae. i.</hi> hiding places. For ſometimes in the heate of perſecution, the Chriſtians, though ſincere, yet either timorous or rather provident, not to be diſturbed at their holy meetings, did aſſemble in Caves in the earth in Woods and deſarts as the Apoſtles themſelves <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iuel. apol. part.</hi> 2. <hi>art.</hi> 3. Ioh. 20. 19. 1 King. 18. 13.</note> when they aſſembled in the night, with the doores ſhut for feare of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and as the Prophets were hidden by fifty in a Cave; by the good <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah.</hi> But O! the goodneſſe of our mercifull God, who hath placed unto us our Churches in moſt open view: and made both the way thither, and our being there, ſafe and comfortable. We neede not with <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> goe to Chriſt by night. The Church doores are open at noone day, wee are in no danger in going to, or being at Church; but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves to puniſhment, by keeping away. <hi>Happy are the eyes which ſee the things which we ſee.</hi> And God give us grace to make good uſe of ſo great bleſſings.</p>
               <p>Churches have alſo the names of Oratories, of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the Latine Word <hi>Orare</hi> to pray. For that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in all their meetings, uſed to prayſe God, and to pray unto him. <hi>Euſebius</hi> writing of the joyfull <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> dayes, with the zeale and devotion of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, before the perſecution began under <hi>Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quis aggregationes multitudinis inſigneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que concurſus ad oratoria deſcriberet? i.</hi> who was able to deſcribe the gathering together of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21996:20"/>
the multitude, and their goodly flocking to the Oratories? And in the next Chapter, lamentably bewailing what their ſinnes had brought upon them, he hath theſe words; <hi>Oratoria a Culmine ad pavimentum uſque deijci, ipſis oculis vidimus. i.</hi> Wee have ſeene with our eyes, the Oratories <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> throwne downe from the toppe to the bottome. And in an other place hee calleth them <hi>Oratoria dominica,</hi> The Lords Oratories, <hi>(i.)</hi> houſes of prayer to the Lord; and thus to call Churches we have good warrant from Gods owne edict, when he ſayd, <hi>Mine houſe ſhall be called an houſe of Prayer, to all Nations:</hi> who goeth to Church, goeth to Gods houſe, to ſpeake to God by prayer, and to heare God ſpeaking unto him by his Word. Looke well to thy feete; take heede thou offer not the Sacrifice of fooles: Be not raſh in ſpeaking, but adviſed and ſerious in thy Petitions. Be not blockiſh nor brutiſh, but reverent and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in thine attention; thou art here in talke with the high God, in his owne houſe and Chamber of preſence.</p>
               <p>Σέμνια is a name alſo given to Churches: of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> word σεμνὸς which ſignifieth reverend, holy or majeſticall, and alludeth to the word of <hi>Iacob,</hi> when he ſayd <hi>how dreadfull is this place? It is none</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>other, than the houſe of God, and gate of heaven.</hi> This is little conſidered or regarded by thoſe people who to profeſſe againſt ſuperſtition, come into the Church with their hands in their pockets, and their hats on their heads; and ſo ſtalke up the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21996:20"/>
Allie, and ſit them downe without any reverence. But to this point more ſhall be ſayd (God willing) in the ninth Chapter.</p>
               <p>Churches ſometimes are called <hi>Martyria,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> either becauſe the Monuments of Martyrs <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruffin. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 27, 28.</note> were placed and preſerved in them; or becauſe they have beene named by the name of ſome Martyr, at their Conſecration, <hi>Martyrii vocabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cent.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Constantini temporibus, cum in Martyrum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morias Templa Conſtruerentur, uſurpari cepit, i.</hi> The word <hi>Martyrie</hi> beganne to be uſed in the dayes of <hi>Canstantine,</hi> when Temples were conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to the memoriall of <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Templa</hi> is often the word for theſe houſes of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> God, the notation of which name, ſome fetch from <hi>tectum</hi> or <hi>tegmen amplum. i.</hi> A large or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple roofe, wherein as in all other parts, it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Churches, to exceede other buildings, as being erected for many to aſſemble in, for the Worſhip of the high God. Others will have them called <hi>Templa, a Contemplando,</hi> becauſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly both for their ſituation, bulke, and lofti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they were to be ſeene and diſcerned a farre off. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith of <hi>Constantine, Civitates quae videbantur vel maximè propter ſplendorem excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Devit. Conſt. l</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 49.</note> 
                  <hi>templis egregiis magnificiſque exornandas Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit. i.</hi> He cauſed thoſe Citties which were ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the goodlieſt, to be adorned with notable and magnificent Temples: and a little after hee <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 51.</note> reciteth the Epiſtle of <hi>Constantine,</hi> to the Biſhops of <hi>Palaeſtine,</hi> to purge the ancient habitation of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21996:21"/>
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> from the Idolatry and impiety, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it had beene prophaned, and of which the Emperour ſaith, <hi>Quem ſane locum decrevimus exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia Templi ſtructura adornare,</hi> we have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to adorne that place with the fabrike of a goodly Temple.</p>
               <p>We finde Churches anciently ſtiled <hi>Baſilicae,</hi> as <hi>Baſilica Sicinini,</hi> the Church of <hi>Sicininus: Baſilicae appellatio, pro templo, frequens eſſe apud Nazianze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruffin. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Cent.</hi> 4. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſium &amp; alios, i. Nazianzen, Ambroſe</hi> and others, doe uſually call a Temple by the name of <hi>Baſilica.</hi> The word <hi>Baſilica</hi> commeth of Βασιλεὺσ a King. <hi>Baſilica</hi> therefore is, as if one ſhould ſay an houſe for a King. For ſo the Church is the houſe of the great King, <hi>viz.</hi> Almighty God, or elſe becauſe Church is ſuch and ſo faire a modell of building, as becommeth no leſſe man than a King. The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe both a Temple and a Pallace; and to this purpoſe ſerve thoſe words of deſcription in <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Ad immenſam celſitudinem erigebantur, i.</hi> Temples or Churches were raiſed up to an huge or wonderfull height.</p>
               <p>Time was when men in Chriſtian humility repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves <hi>duſt and aſhes, wormes and no men:</hi> and thought it no reaſon that themſelves ſhould dwell in magnificent Pallaces, whilſt the Arke of God is <note place="margin">2 Sam. 7. 2.</note> lodged in a booth<hi>:</hi> and therefore we ſee that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently there were built for God, <hi>Templa &amp; Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae, i.</hi> Sumptuous and goodly Churches: for let us now behold thoſe Churches, which the devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21996:21"/>
and Pietie of our Fathers of old have ſet up; and we ſhall eaſily perceive, if we compare them with the private habitations and halls, even of great nobilities, erected in thoſe dayes: that Churches then might well beare the names of <hi>Templa</hi> and <hi>Baſilicae. i.</hi> Lofty and Royall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. But when we obſerve how private mens houſes, of the later editions, doe towre it up, and advance their roofes to ſuch an height, as quite in ercepts and ſcreenes up, the proſpect of the houſes of God in the Land. How the Pallaces of Knights and Gentlemen, draw all mens eyes upon them, whilſt the poore Church over-topped with her Patrons Pyramids, ſtandeth cringing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, as a ſhamed to be ſeene, ſo tattered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in her roofe, walls, and windowes<hi>:</hi> ſo duſty, fullied, and forlorne within, as that the ſtone doth cry out of the wall, and the beame out of the Timber doth anſwere it; and both complaine of an irreligious age, producing men who thinke not God worthy of ſo good houſes as their owne<hi>:</hi> how divers particular men in a Pariſh, beſtow uſually every one of them more upon their owne houſes, than all of them together will lay out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the houſe of God: we muſt needes thinke that this is an impietie, which to the ſhame of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, hath too long and too much prevailed. But God be thanked who hath put it into the heart of his ſacred Majeſty, our dread Soveraigne, and given zeale to our Eccleſiaſticall governors, under
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21996:22"/>
him, to looke better into the condition of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; whereby a bleſſed reformation is begun. The Lord God, for whoſe glory they are ſo affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, encreaſe their zeale and proſper their pious endevours: that we may behold the houſe and Worſhip of God reduced to the Priſtine and due eſteeme and ſplendor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. VII. <hi>That to aſcribe holineſſe unto Churches; to build them faire; and to adorne them; is neither Popiſh, nor any way Superſtitious.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Brethren who brooke not that Churches ſhould be deemed and uſed as holy: cry out, that thus to reſpect Churches, is Popiſh and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious. But they ſhew not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Superſtition or Popery conſiſteth. But deale herein like men that cry theeves, theeves<hi>:</hi> and yet neither tell who, nor what manner of men theſe theeves are. So theſe people doe as it were follow Superſtion and Popery, with hue and cry, all the World over; but they doe not deſcribe or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21996:22"/>
ſet forth this ſuperſtition and Popery; ſo that when we meete it, in our Churches, in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration and uſage of them (in all which they ſay it is) we may know it, and deale therewith as becommeth us.</p>
               <p>Shall I tell them (what I am taught) that ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition is in Greeke called Δεισιδαιμονία: which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth <note place="margin">Plut. in Alex.</note> 
                  <hi>Deos eſſe metu credere. i.</hi> through feare to beleeve that there are Gods, <hi>animum ſtolida timidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate complens. i.</hi> When the heart is fraught with fooliſh feare. Or to ſpeake with <hi>Nazianzen: ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitio eſt meticuloſe Deum colere,</hi> to worſhip God timorouſly. To this effect Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, uſing the word in the adjective and comparative degree, Δεισιδαιμονεςέρ<g ref="char:ougr">ȣ</g>ς as if he ſhould have ſayd, fearing God more than you neede. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are the words of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> who having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared out of the Gloſſe, that <hi>ſuperſtitio est relligo,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>a.</hi> 2 <hi>ae. q.</hi> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>ultra modum ſervata. i.</hi> Superſtition is Religion, maintained beyond meaſure; doth after declare it to be, <hi>vitium religioni, oppoſitum, ſecundum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum. i.</hi> A vice oppoſite to Religion in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: as if he ſhould ſay too much Religion<hi>:</hi> and then leaſt it ſhould be imagined, that a man may be too Religious; he explaineth himſelfe and telleth us, that he doth not call ſuperſtition Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in any other ſence, than by way of Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor; becauſe it ſeemeth ſo, or lookes ſomething like unto religion. As when a crafty Mate is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a wiſe fellow. And therefore afterwards hee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21996:23"/>
calleth it <hi>ſimulata religio,</hi> counterfeit Religion. Againe, he ſtateth ſuperſtition to conſiſt either in the Object, as when the Creature is worſhipped in ſtead of the Creator: or elſe in the manner of performance, whereof hee giveth this inſtance. If a man now under the Goſpell would worſhip the true God, with the Leviticall forme and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</p>
               <p>And though I conceive that any kinde of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion may be referred, to one of theſe two heads: yet to endeavour the further clearing of this point, I will give one other diſtinction of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, <hi>viz.</hi> Superſtition is either obſerving or abſtaining. The firſt member of this diſtinction I take from the words of Saint <hi>Paul, Ye obſerve dayes, and moneths, and times, and yeares.</hi> Vpon <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 10.</note> which words, a learned interpreter noting a foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold obſervation of times. 1. Phyſicall. 2. Civill. 3. Eccleſiaſticall. 4. Superſtitious, ſaith, this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious <note place="margin">Heming.</note> obſervation of times is, <hi>quando opinio cultus, meriti, justitiae &amp; neceſsitatis accedit. i.</hi> When men have a conceite that one day maketh them more acceptable to God than another, with whom agreeth Maſter <hi>Calvin,</hi> ſaying upon the ſame text; <hi>Libera apud nos eſt &amp; omni ſuperſtitione pura obſervatio. i.</hi> The obſervation of times with us, is free, and without Superſtition: as if he ſhould ſay, we doe not aſcribe any vertue, efficacie, lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or Piety unto one day or time, more than to another.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21996:23"/>
The other member of the diſtinction, <hi>viz.</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining Superſtition, I take from the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where he ſaith; <hi>touch not, taſte not, handle not,</hi> Which words, <hi>Zanchie</hi> with other interpretors, reading, <hi>Eate not, taſte not, handle not,</hi> maketh this Obſervation. <hi>Indicat Apoſtolus inſatiabilem ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitioſorum hominum in condendis novis obſervatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus libidinem. i.</hi> The Apoſtle ſheweth how eager ſuperſtitious men are in coyning new obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. <hi>Hemingius</hi> alſo on theſe words ſaith: theſe are the words of the falſe Apoſtles, <hi>quibus Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitoſe decreta cumularunt. i.</hi> Wherewith they have ſuperſtitiouſly multiplyed decrees. The words of <hi>Piſcator</hi> on this place are <hi>ſuperſtitioſorum cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum exprimit. i.</hi> The Apoſtle ſetteth forth the diſpoſition of ſuperſtitious people, afrayd to touch, taſte, or handle, thoſe things in the tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, taſting, and handling whereof there is no ſinne nor any danger. Of this abſtayning ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition I may ſay as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes of ſome men, <hi>they were in great feare, were no feare was,</hi> which <note place="margin">Pſal. 53. 5.</note> very thing in effect, S. <hi>Gregory</hi> applyeth to theſe kinde of ſuperſtious people, ſaying <hi>Superſtitioſus omnia timet, terram, mare, aerem, caelum, tenebras, lumen, ſtrepitum, ſilentium, ſomnum. i.</hi> The ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious <note place="margin">In moral.</note> man ſtands in feare of every thing, of the earth, of the water, of the ayre, of the skye, of the darkeneſſe, of the light, of noyſe, of ſilence, and of his owne dreames, ſutable whereto are the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21996:24"/>
words of the Philoſopher. <hi>Qui ſuperſtitione im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butus est, quietus eſſe nunquam potest. i.</hi> The ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious man is ever reſtleſſe, or of an unquiet Spirit. For as it is in <hi>Curtius, humanarum mentium ludibrium ſuperſtitio. i.</hi> Superſtition is the very foolery of the mindes of men, for it is like a ſcare Crow in the braine, and maketh a man afrayd of his owne ſhadow, as he that durſt not looke out, for feare the skye ſhould fall.</p>
               <p>Now then, having thus deſcribed ſuperſtition, and given you his true markes, whereby you may know him, when you meete him: Let us betake ourſelves to the purſuite and ſearch, ſome where among us this theefe doth lurke; and I doubt not but to finde him out, and bring him to light before we have done. And herein I will deale as <hi>Laban</hi> did, when he ſought his loſt Idols, he made ſearch firſt in the tents of <hi>Iacob, Leah,</hi> and the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maydes; <note place="margin">Gen. 31.</note> and when he found them not there hee went to ranſacke in the Tent of <hi>Rachel,</hi> where hee might have found them, if he had not beene too credulous. And I meane to enter firſt into the Tents of <hi>Iacob, Leah,</hi> and the handmayds, that is, the Cathedrall and Parochian Churches. And that my brethren may ſee faire play, I doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt them to goe along with me<hi>:</hi> and if they perceive mee to paſſe by any Corner unſought, and then to call mee backe to a more carefull ſearch.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21996:24"/>
And in this courſe, we cannot but begin with the Church yards, of Cathedrall and Parochian Churches. And being here, in the open ayre, I deſire to know what ſuperſtition is here to bee either diſcerned or imagined? Maſter <hi>Carth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> is angry with them; yet all that he hath <note place="margin">
                     <hi>T. C. pag.</hi> 50. § 6. 7. <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>dives.</hi> 7.</note> to ſay againſt them is but this<hi>:</hi> That as they came in with the Monke, ſo they might have gone out with him, for all the good they doe. The Monke which he meanes is <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> of whom <hi>Damaſus</hi> ſaith, that he was a Monke. But <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith that he was a Prieſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> and then <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> when as yet the Biſhops and Church of <hi>Rome</hi> flouriſhed in exemplary <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anno.</hi> 266.</note> faith and probitie. But whether <hi>Dionyſius</hi> were a Monke or a Prieſt before he was Pope, and whether Church-yards (the conſtitution where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is very ancient, as appeareth by <hi>Athanaſius</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Athan. apol.</note> and others) were firſt ſet out by <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe, to prove in them, or in the uſe of them, any ſuperſtition. They are conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated with the Church unto God; as being the Courts of the Lords houſe. And have beene anciently uſed and yet may be, not onely for Dormitories or burialls, but alſo for divine worſhip, and have borne the name of Oratories for there they did hold Synods, ſing Pſalmes, <note place="margin">Dur. deritibs.</note> and adminiſter the Sacraments.</p>
               <p>And before we enter into any of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21996:25"/>
we may in the Church yard, take notice of the quarrell, which our brethren make to the very ſituation of them; as having their fore part or upper end, ſtanding alwayes to the Eaſt. Of whom I aske, and why not to the Eaſt? Is there any danger, in ſetting the upper end of a Church into the Eaſt? Or is there any Commandement againſt it? If we aſcribed any holineſſe to the Eaſt, more than to any other quarter; or that wee deemed any Church or Chappell unholy, for not being placed ſo into the Eaſt<hi>:</hi> then might this be accounted a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious obſervation of the Eaſt. But when this is now done in imitation of the practiſe of Primitive times, continued unto this preſent. And for order and conformitie of one Church with another: And it may be for ſome docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſignification<hi>:</hi> as that we under the Goſpell looke into the Eaſt, as acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Sonne of righteouſneſſe to have ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen unto us, and to bee ſhining upon us, with light and comfort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas the Temple for Leviticall worſhip looked Weſtward, as it were towards the night, in token of the Clouds and darkeneſſe under which the people were at that time. Theſe and divers other good conſiderations might there bee in the firſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of our Churches in this manner without touch of ſuperſtition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21996:25"/>
But I am tould, that when we are within the Church, we find it divided, and a partition or ſome marke of diſtinction ſet between the Church and the Chancell, as we call it; and one part of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is to be read in one place, and another in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Wee are now entred into the Church, and wee find it indeed as here it is deſcribed. But as yet we find no Superſtition. Diſtinctions of ſeverall places in the houſe of God are not any conceit, crept in with Poperie: but ſuch as have been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and put in ure, very early in the Primitive Church, by what partitions or boundaries eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them was ſevered from other I cannot ſo fully finde out, neither is it materiall. Only, this is agreeable with good reaſon, order and comelines, free from any colour of Superſtition: that as there be ſeverall rancks of people, profeſſing Church-uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo they have their places in their ſeverall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Some are unworthy to Come within the doores of the Church and therefore are to ſtand without. Some are fit to be received in, to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized: Some to be inſtructed in the grounds of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and to repaire with the reſt of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: All which is done in the nave and body of the Church. And as men profit in knowledge, and a working Faith, to diſcerne the Lords body They are admitted into a higher roome; where the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the body and blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is to be adminiſtred, at the holy Table, in the Chancell: which devideth it from the reſt of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21996:26"/>
Seeing then, there are ſeverall offices orduties to be performed in the Church: what Superſtition is it, if there be diſtinct and ſeverall places for them? If all places be by nature holy alike; and by Conſecration, the whol Chuch and every part thereof be ſet apart, for Gods worſhip: Then why is it not as lawfull to pray in one place thereof as in another? Is it lawfull and and no Superſtition, to pray ſometimes in the Desk or reading pew, and ſometimes in the Pulpit, and ſometimes at the Font? why then may not it be as free from offence, to pray ſometimes at the Communion Table, and yet in a fift or ſixt place if the Church require it at our hands.</p>
               <p>And whereas our bretheren ſay, that one part of the Service is read in one place, and another part in another place, they are miſtaken. For thoſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which are read at the Communion Table, are not ſeverall parts of the ſame, but are diſtinct Services; and ſo are they called the firſt and ſecond ſervice. The firſt hath been antiently called <hi>matutinae,</hi> and by Contraction <hi>Mattins,</hi> or the early Service, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto came al that would, being not excommunicated, into the nave or body of the Church. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended the faſhion was, after a while to give warning by a ſmall bell: And then the ſecond Service beganne, at the Communion Table: At which the company antiently was the fewer, <hi>demiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Catechumenorum turba,</hi> the Company of thoſe that were not yet fit for the Communion, being ſent away. In that therefore, we have the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21996:26"/>
Service at the Communion Table this is no Superſtition: but an orderly ſorting of the place to the buſineſſe after the example of the purer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouter times; whereto we are reduced from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, that theſe latter dayes have produced. The Miniſter, before he beginneth the Communion, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up into the pulpit with an Homily or Sermon to prepare the Communicants (I hope no body will find fault that a Sermon is made in the Pulpit) which ended, the Miniſter returneth to proceed in that which concerneth the Communion, at the Table for the Communion.</p>
               <p>If we held, that ſome prayers were not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God: except they were made preciſely in this or that place: Or if we reputed the Supper of the Lord uneffectuall; if it be not received in the Chancell: then here were ſuperſtition. But when we do thinges not upon any ſuch fancy: but in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and conformity to diſcipline and order, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and comelyneſſe; we are no way to be, either taxed or ſuſpected, for Superſtition. Why is it not as free from Superſtition to adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in one place of the Church, and to pray in an other, as to pray in one place, and to preach in an other? and to baptize in a third? Why is it not Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition for the people to draw nere to receive the Holy Sacrament, to their comfort at the Holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; more then for the Miniſter to walke up and downe the Church, and to Crowde into thronged ſtooles with the ſacred body and blood of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in his handes?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21996:27"/>
In the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming up to the holy Table where is their ſpiritual food made ready for them is no Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: But in the miniſters going ſo, from ſtool to ſtool, or pew to pew there is much irreverence &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, ill beſeeming the adminiſtration of ſuch a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. (O my bretheren) you are not called up to worſhip any, but the true God: nor to worſhip the true God, after any manner, otherwiſe then God requireth <hi>meekly kneeling upon your knees.</hi> Some have grudged to receive the holy communion knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: But that errour hath long ſince been diſcovered and reformed: and now you take a new offence, not at the poſture of the body, but the place where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is at the rayle, before the Communion Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Do you not know and confeſſe that the word, the Sacrament and Prayer be of equal uſe and power in all places: not as the place, but as the Grace of God ſhall give the bleſſing? What Superſtition is it to kneele at the rayle more then at thy ſtoole? or what ſinne is it to leane upon the one more then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other? Only I ſhould thinke, that the neerer a man approacheth to that table, whereupon he <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with his eyes</hi> the ſacred body &amp; blood of his Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> layd forth for him, to feede upon, to everlaſting life: the more ſhould he find himſelfe raviſhed with devotion &amp; not skared with an immagination of Superſtition.</p>
               <p>But wee ſee already in many Churches (and do feare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſhortly we ſhall behold the like in all) the Communion Table mounted up and elevated di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſtepps or degrees, and encloaſed with rayles<hi>:</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:21996:27"/>
But the font which is the laver of regeneration ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the lower end of the Church and left open to the allyes.</p>
               <p>All this is true and yet ye may be without feare, that in all this there is not any Superſtition. For ſtill, here is neither any falſe God worſhiped, nor any falſe manner of worſhip in all this: But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the party to be baptized is to be entred or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into the Congregation; the font or laver, by the which he muſt be admitted, ſtandeth beneath at the entrance of the Church, ready to receive and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayne him. There is he made one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe, which have right and intereſt in the priviledges of that part of the Church, where the font is placed: <hi>viz.</hi> the water of Baptiſme to waſh away his ſinnes the word for his inſtruction, and prayer, whereby to Communicate himſelfe to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God untill he be fitted to be further prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the holy Table. which is therefore elevated or ſet downe upon an higher floore then the reſt of the pavement; to be the more in the eyes and view of the people: that ſo for their edification they may the better behold the behaviour of the Preiſt, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating and ſetting apart the elements to become a Sacrament. And that the very ſight of the holy Table, at all times, may beget in the beholders an hunger and thirſt after that bleſſed food. The Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is incloſed with rayles, to Preſerve it from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes whereto elſe it would be ſubject. In which caſe the Church antiently uſed to be very carefull. And if (as in ſome Churches it is) the font were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21996:28"/>
with rayles encloſed: it were (I ſpeake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der correction) more ſuteable to the reverence due thereunto.</p>
               <p>But to proceed in our Search. Let us looke well about<hi>:</hi> leaſt any nooke yet ſhrowde ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. Here are the Kings armes ſet up: not for any matter of divine worſhip: But to profeſſe and teſtifie the ſubjection of every ſoule to the higher power. For as the written ſentences upon the walls by letters, ſo theſe Scutchions, by their expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, do put us in minde of that <hi>Defender of the Faitb,</hi> and of our duty to him, who is <hi>next and immediately under God, ſupream governor over al perſons and cauſes as well eccleſiaſticall as Temporall in all his Majeſties Realmes &amp; Dominions.</hi> And in all this there is no Superſtition.</p>
               <p>O but looke (ſayth one) upon the Church win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and then tell me, what meane thoſe images <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> and pictures which are in the glaſſe?</p>
               <p>They are not there ſet, for any matter of worſhip of either God Saint or Angell; but for hiſtory and ornament. No Chriſtian (ſo far as I know) holdeth <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> it unlawfull to make an image, or to uſe for memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, Cogniſance, Hiſtory or Ornament. For if it were utterly unlawfull to make an image there ſhould not have been ſo many, yea any at al in the Temple or Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bernacle: Neither would God have taught <hi>Aholiah</hi> and <hi>Bezaliel</hi> the making of them. For, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things in the Tabernacle and Temple were typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: yet might nothing be there, which was againſt the Morall law, or in it ſelfe evill and unlawfull. And many things were there, as well for ornament
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21996:28"/>
and decency as for typicall ſignification. Images <note place="margin">Tert. Bazil. Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Aug. Cyril. Greg. Euſeb. Chriſ. Juſtin. Orig. Nazian.</note> then may be made; they have been made: and by the Primitive Churches frequently uſed, in their Churches &amp; Chalices; no word of God prohibiteth the ſetting of them up in Churches<hi>:</hi> we performe no worſhip unto them nor to any other by them. And therefore their being in our Churches is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Leviticall nor Superſtitious.</p>
               <p>It is too poore a conceit for any to faſten ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon our Churches, becauſe of that which the Papiſts do practiſe in theirs. For, what is Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious among them, wee leave unto them. And wee performe only that, which is lawfull, decent and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The Papiſts do in many things, the ſame which wee do, but we omit many things, though not all things, which they practice, we looke not to the actions of Papiſts, for our direction: but to the word of God and practice of antient and Orthodox Chriſtians, where the Papiſt is ſo guided wee gladly approve him, and do as he doth, where he innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and ſwarveth from this rule; we are ſory for him, and there leave him. We think not the worſe of any true Doctrine, Chriſtian act, or devout deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, for that a Papiſt doth or maintaine the one, or performe the other. But we thinke the better of a Papiſt the neerer he commeth to truth and devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the like courſe we hold with others: ſo long, and no longer to hold with them, as in Doctrine &amp; practice they are devout and Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>If any take exception, againſt any rich furniture and utenſill in our Churches: and tell us of ſome
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21996:29"/>
Superſtition in them: I wiſh that our brethen could as well ſhew us our Churches ſo rightly furniſhed; as we can cleare them from being therein Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. In moſt of our Churches, beſides the bible, the Service or Common Prayer booke, with the apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, the Preiſts veſtments (meane inough a pewter flagon, and a ſilver cup: what have we elſe: except wee will rekon the bels in the ſteeple? How many meane yomen be there in many pariſhes in England, whoſe plate and rich ſtuffe is more worth, then all the whol furniture of his Pariſh church? In ſome great Pariſhes, in rich Corporations, as alſo in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers (but not in all) Cathedrall Churches there is ſome better proviſion to adorne the Church, to ſet out the Service and commend our profeſſion: of which, though ſome grudging ſay (which you know who) <hi>what needeth this waſte?</hi> yet is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no Superſtition. For, was there any Superſtition in them that brought ſilver &amp; gold for the uſe of the Tabernacle, or Onix ſtone and other pretious ſtones for the Ephod; more then in them, that beſtowed but Rames skins or goates hayre? if any ſay that theſe things were for Leviticall worſhip: I muſt requeſt them to underſtand, that the Leviticalneſſe of things of the Tabernacle, or Temple conſiſted not in their materials, as gold ſilver or the like; but in their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picall relation to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and things in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be fulfilled. Againe, was it Superſtition in the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Eaſt to bring out of their treaſures, and to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. 7.</note> preſent unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Gold Frankincence and Myrhe, more then if they had beſtowed on him ſome chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21996:29"/>
commodity: was it Superſtition in the woman to power on the head of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>a box ful of very pretious oyntment,</hi> or in her that <hi>annoyntted his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 12. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>feete with coſtly Spicknard,</hi> more then if ſhe had bathed them in faire water? No. But as devout and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people, they expreſſed their love and good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The like we ſay of them that embalmed his dead body<hi>:</hi> And ſo of them which are at coſt in adorning and beautifying the houſe of God, and enriching the <hi>place where his honour dwelleth:</hi> or in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at charge with thoſe things which belong to his worſhip: wherein we place no ſuperſtition or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: but only acknowledge and endevor our duty and thankfulneſſe, our reſpect and devotion to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God: according to the meaſure wherewith God hath enabled us.</p>
               <p>It is true that S. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſeemeth ſomething ſharp, againſt the adorning of Churches. But withall, the truth is, he doth not condemne the thing it ſelf; for, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 8. <hi>ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metr.</hi>
                  </note> ſo he ſaith of it: <hi>non ab nuo, non reprehendo.</hi> I diſclaime it not, I reprehend it not. But the Fathers heate is againſt ſuch men, as pleaſed themſelves with the only wals and outward ſplendor of Churches, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſ.</hi> 1. 11, 12. <hi>c.</hi>
                  </note> in the meane time neither faith nor charity. As when almighty God diſclaimeth the externall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious doings of Hypocrites, wanting true piety, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Helid.</hi>
                  </note> and common honeſty. For, that S. <hi>Jerome</hi> did not diſlike the adorning and beautifying of Churches, appeareth, in that he commendeth Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potian for being carefull, <hi>Si niteret altare, templi parie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes eſſent abſque fuligine pavimenta terſa, &amp; quod baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21996:30"/>
                  <hi>diverſis floribus, arborum comis, atque vitium pampi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis adumbrabat. i.</hi> That the Altar might be kept neat the wals faire, the floore cleane, and for that he did ſet forth the Churches with various flowers, boughs of trees and vine branches. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth <hi>Gorgonias quod ſumptuoſis donariis templa ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornaverat. i.</hi> that he had beſtowed coſtly gifts upon <note place="margin">Orat. in Lan. Gorg.</note> the adorning of Churches. <hi>Optatus</hi> reporteth that even in the dayes of <hi>Maxentius</hi> there were very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ornaments for the Churches of Africa. And he commendeth the Emperour <hi>Conſtans</hi> for that when he ſent almes into Africa, for the poore: he ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>ad parm. l.</hi> 3.</note> alſo ornaments for the Churches. So, his piety and his charity went hand in hand.</p>
               <p>Shall wee imagine that God enriching the world with ſilver, and gold and pretious ſtones, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtined <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hooker. l.</hi> 5. <hi>ſect.</hi> 15.</note> theſe, only to ſet out ſecular pomp and ſtate: &amp; will have none but the baſeſt of his creatures to be imployed in his own ſervice? as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and other learned countrimen of ours lately an ſwering an accuſation of the Papiſts, who would have the world beleeve, that we waver in our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and leane to Popery, becauſe of the coſt now more then of late, beſtowed in beautifying of our Churches: hath a paſſage ſo apt to this our purpoſe <note place="margin">Chillin hic. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. of proteſt. in prefac.</note> as I thinke fit to tranſcribe it at full, in theſe words: <q>What if out of devotion towards God and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that he ſhould be worſhiped as <hi>in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> in the firſt place: ſo alſo <hi>in the beauty of holyneſſe?</hi> What if out of feare, that too much ſimplicity and nakedneſſe in the publique worſhip
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21996:30"/>
of God, may beget in the ordinary ſort of men, a dull and ſtupide irreverence, and out of hope that the outward ſtate and glory of it, being well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and wiſely moderated, may ingender, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, increaſe and nouriſh the inward reverence, reſpect, and devotion, which is due unto Gods Soveraigne Majeſty and power? What if out of a perſwaſion and deſire, that Papiſts may be wonne over to us the ſooner, by the removing of this ſcandall out of their way, and out of an holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, that the weaker ſort of Proteſtantes might be the eaſier ſeduced unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the magnificence and pompe of their Church Service, in caſe it were not removed? I ſay, what if out of theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations the Governours of our Church, of late, more then formerly, have ſet themſelves to adorn and beautifie the places, where <hi>Gods Honour dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,</hi> and to make them as heavenly as they can, with outward ornaments? Is this a ſigne that they are warping towards Poperie? Is this devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Church of England an argument, that ſhe is comming over to the Church of Rome? Sr <hi>Edwyn Sandys</hi> I preſume (further ſaith the author) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man will grant had no inclination that way; yet he 40 yeares ſince, commended this part of de votion in Papiſts, and makes no ſcruple of propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, to the imitation of Proteſtantes.</q> His words are.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>This one thing I cannot but highly commend in that</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Survay of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion imit.</note> 
                     <hi>ſort and order, they ſpare nothing, which either coſt can performe in enriching, or skill in adorning, the Temple</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21996:31"/>
                     <hi>of God: or to ſet out his ſervice, with the greateſt pompe &amp; magificence that can be deviſed. And although for the moſt part, much baſneſſe and childiſhneſſe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in the Maſters and contrivers of thoſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: yet this outward ſtate and glory being well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, doth ingender, quicken, increaſe and nouriſh the inward reverence, reſpect and devotion, which is due unto Soveraigne Majesty and Power. And although I am not ignorant, that many men well reputed, have embraced the thirſty opinion of that diſciple, who thought all to be waſted that was beſtowed upon Chriſt, in that ſorte: and that it were much better beſtowed on him in the poore (yet with an eye perhappes, that themſelves would be his quarter Almoners) Notwithſtanding I muſt confeſſe, it will never ſinke into my heart, that in proportion of reaſon, the allowance for furniſhing out the Service of God, ſhould be meaſured by the ſcant and ſtrickt rule of meere neceſſity (a proportion ſo low, that nature to other moſt bountifull in matter of neceſſity hath not failed, no not the moſt ignoble creatures of the world) and that for our ſelves no meaſure of heaping, but the moſt we can ſet. No rule of expence, but to the utmoſt pompe we list: Or that God himſelfe had ſo enriched the lower partes of the world with ſuch woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull variety of beauty &amp; glory, that they might ſerve only to the pampering of mortall man in his pride; and that in the Service of the high Creator, Lord and giver (the outward glory of whoſe higher palace may appeare by the very Lampes that we ſee ſo farre off, burning glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly in it) only the ſimpler, baſer, cheaper, leſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, leſſe beautifull, leſſe glorious things, ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21996:31"/>
                     <hi>Eſpecially, ſeeing as in princes courtes, ſo in the Service of God alſo, this outward ſtate and glory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well diſpoſed, doth (as I have ſaid) ingender, quicken, increaſe and nouriſh the inward reverence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and devotion which is due to Soveraigne Majeſty and power, which thoſe whom the uſe thereof cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade unto would eaſily by the want thereof, be brougbt to confeſſe: for which cauſe, I crave leave to be excuſed by them herein, if, in zeale to the common Lord of all; I chooſe rather to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the vertue of an enemy: then to flatter the vice and imbecillity of a friend.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Finally I know not any that diſſallow the ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Churches except Anabaptiſts and Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes; into whoſe ſchiſme and faction too many of our bretheren ſeem to be too much inclining. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> the unfaithfull diſciple afore mentioned did grudge at what was beſtowed on Chriſt; and came not into the bagge, which he had in keeping. And wee read of one Felix an apoſtate and great treaſurer to the apoſtate Emperour <hi>Julian,</hi> who beholding the goodly veſſels which the piety of the good <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine and Conſtantius</hi> had beſtowed upon the Church: ſayd in the bitterneſſe of his malice: <hi>en quibus vaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s miniſtratur Mariae filio. i.</hi> Behold what goodly veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels the ſonne of <hi>Mary</hi> is ſerved in? But as the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry relateth; this ſonne of <hi>Beltal</hi> quickly came to a ſhamefull end.</p>
               <p>To adorne Churches is not Superſtitious: but to deprive them of their ornaments, to hinder their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, and to repine thereat, are all, no better then ſacrilegious.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21996:32"/>
And now me thinks I heare ſome of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren call upon me, to liſten to the ſounde that is made in our Churches, by voices of ſingers, by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes and other inſtruments of muſique, and to tell how I can cleare this from being Popiſh or ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious?</p>
               <p>But God be thanked: as there is no law to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit the uſe of muſique, even in the Church Service: ſo withall, being rightly uſed, it is very uſefull and profitable, for the ſpirituall man, in that it ſtirreth up his chriſtian affection, the more chearefully to prayſe God. <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi> ſaith that in Muſique rightly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd. judic.</hi> 5.</note> ordered <hi>tria bonorum genera concurrunt: honeſtum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, jueundum. i.</hi> three good things concur <hi>viz.</hi> come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profitable and pleaſant. When God had brought his people through the red ſea: &amp; therein whelmed the Aegyptians<hi>:</hi> The Iſraelites; as they expreſſe their gladneſſe, by their ſongs<hi>:</hi> ſo, to proportion their joy, the beſt they can, to the meaſure of their hapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe do ſet their ditty to an inſtrument of Muſique. The like is done by devoute <hi>Deborah.</hi> For when God had given the life of <hi>Siſerah</hi> into the hands of <hi>Jael;</hi> and peace to Iſrael, in the confuſion of <hi>Jabin: Then ſung Deborah and Barak: prayſe yee the Lord for a venging Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this was done once upon ſpeciall occaſion, at the red Sea, &amp; not above once more, in nere two hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> yeares, in the dayes of the Judges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what is this then, to the ſtanding uſe of muſique in the publique worſhip of God?</p>
               <p>But this was done in the publique worſhip of God <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21996:32"/>
by the people of god; without any breach of any law of God, &amp; therfore it is ſtil lawful to be done again as well twice as once; &amp; as well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly as ſometimes. And therefore the King and prophet <hi>David</hi> the only man ever Chronicled to have been <hi>a man after Gods owne heart</hi> (and well might he ſo be, being ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as he was for the houſe and honour of God) as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69. 9.</note> he compoſed his Pſalmes, to be tuned and ſung to ſeverall inſtruments of Muſique, for Gods honor; ſo he brought that muſique into the Church, and erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chro. ea.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; Ca.</hi> 25.</note> the moſt glorious Quire that ever was under the cope of Heaven: <hi>for ſong in the houſe of the Lord: with Cymballs, Pſalteries and Harpes for the Service of the houſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this was in the old Teſtement and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> is like to have beene ſome Leviticall Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               <p>The is no ſuch Inſtitution among all the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> ceremonies which were all delivered by God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and by Moſes to the people, 400 yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> was borne. Yea, the text telleth us, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 25. 6.</note> playnely that this was according <hi>to the Kings order.</hi> And therefore, it is no Leviticall ceremony in that there was no inſtitution thereof before the dayes of <hi>David.</hi> And then I hope here is no feare of Popery to be in the uſe of the Church Muſique becauſe it had the firſt Inſtitution in the dayes of <hi>David:</hi> 1500 yeares before any Popery began. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <note place="margin">Eph.</note> as it were in approbation of ſo good a practiſe, <note place="margin">Coloſ.</note> our Saviour Chriſt with his Diſciples ſing a Pſalme at the end of the Sacred Supper. And S. <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:21996:33"/>
adviſeth the uſe of the Pſalmes <hi>hymnes and ſpirituall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comm. Judic. c.</hi> 5. <hi>N.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Songs. Pet. Mart.</hi> proveth that muſique hath beene of uſe in the Chriſtian Church from the dayes of the Apoſtles, becauſe <hi>Plinius ſecundus</hi> writeth unto <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>euſeb. l.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 30</note> that the Chriſtians did <hi>hymnos antelucanos Chriſto ſuo canere i.</hi> Sing Pſalmes to their Chriſt, before day light. They found themſelves thereby char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Gods worſhip. And I do aſſure my ſelfe, that man who ſhal bring to the Church, where Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que is rightly uſed, a devout hart not perverted with prejudice<hi>:</hi> and attend unto the Prayſes of God which are ſet out with Muſique: cannot chooſe but feele his thoughts therewith elevated and enlarged, the more pathetically and feelingly, the more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, and fervently to acknowledge and magnifie the goodneſſe of God. It is true that ſome of the antient Fathers do find fault with the abuſe of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſique in Gods Worſhip: but that condemneth not the right uſe thereof, any more then the <hi>holy Supper</hi> is condemned by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> whileſt he blameth thoſe who ſhamefully prophaned it.</p>
               <p>In the right uſe therefore of church Muſique, there is good profit, and edification to the affection but no Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21996:33"/>
               <head>CAP. VIII. <hi>Gods Servants are Holy and not Superſtitious.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ouſes are uſually framed to ſuit their owners: eſpecially when they build them for their owne habitation. And <hi>ſuch maſters, ſuch men. Salomon</hi> had not only builded an houſe anſweareable to the wiſdome and ſtate of ſo great a King: but was alſo ſorted with ſervants ſuitable to the wiſedome <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 2.</note> of their prince, and to the order and magnificence of his houſe and throne. And God (whoſe <hi>houſe and habitation</hi> the Church is) is holy. The Church alſo being Gods houſe, is holy. So the holy God hath an holy houſe, as is ſuitable. Neither will he want anſwerable ſervants, who by their holy deme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nure ſhall manifeſt it to the world, that they are the <hi>Servants of the holy God.</hi> The true ſervants of God muſt be holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For, the Lord God their <hi>maſter is holy.</hi> And St. Peter telleth us, that we are an <hi>holy Nation.</hi> And here we do not meane only a relative holineſſe, ſuch as times places, garments and the like are capable of: but ſuch an holineſſe as is wrought by the holy Ghoſt in the reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21996:34"/>
And this holineſſe is either inhaeſive or expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In haeſive holineſſe</hi> is that ſeaſoning and gratious conſtitution, wherewith the heart and conſcience is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.</note> inwardly ſo qualified, by the holy Ghoſt as diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it wholy to the will, honour and glory of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. And this is it which <hi>David</hi> hunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after, when he ſaid. <hi>Create in me a mew heart, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>renew a right ſpirit within mee.</hi> Yea this is that Image <hi>of God, according whereunto man</hi> was fiſt created, <hi>in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Expreſſive holineſſe is the outward manifeſtation of the former,</hi> by the words of our mouthes, and by the performances and geſtures of the reſt of the lymbes of our bodyes: as in their ſeverall kindes we be occaſioned, to make uſe of them and this is fully required at our hands Ro. 12. 1. <hi>preſent your bodyes a living Sacrafice holy and acceptable unto God.</hi> This <hi>expreſſive holineſſe is to be practiſed</hi> two wayes. Firſt in our conninuall converſation before God. Secondly in our ſpeciall approaching unto God. As the duty of a Servant to his Maſter is, firſt in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diligent and faithfull in all his buſineſſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in his reſpective behaviour, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to his Maſters preſence: or is in ſpeach with him: and yet more ſpecially, when he is to crave favor, or to give thankes for favors received from him. So the Servant of God, having his heart poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the feare of God, is firſt very carefull, that he offend not in the tounge: that there be no pride nor luſt in his eyes: that his <hi>feete neither walke</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21996:34"/>
                  <hi>nor ſtand in the way of the ungodly:</hi> that his hands be free from bribery, oppreſſion and all iniquity. And finally that all his <hi>members be inſtruments of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto God:</hi> and his <hi>converſation honeſt before the world:</hi> That his <hi>light may ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee his good workes and glorifie his father which is in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath made as well the body as the ſoule. And therefore he is to be ſerved, as well by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward members of the body as by the inward abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule. He that ſaith by <hi>Solomon, Sonne give me thine heart.</hi> Saith alſo by Saint <hi>Paul, preſent your bodyes a living ſacrifice.</hi> And as there muſt <hi>bee no ſtrife among the members:</hi> ſo, neither muſt the ſoule and bodye diſagree, But joyne ſweetly, both <note place="margin">1 <hi>cor.</hi> 6. 20.</note> as one in the Service of God. And therefore he ſaith <hi>Glorifie God in your bodyes and ſpirits</hi> for they are Gods. And of all this, we muſt be conſtantly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16. 8.</note> ſo to <hi>ſet God alwayes before our eyes, and to have alwayes a good conſcience both towards God and towards</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>man,</hi> that when we come to give an accompt <hi>of our Stewardſhip</hi> we may with joy heare that comfortable approbation, of our Lord and Maſter <hi>well done good and faithfull ſervant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when the ſervant of God approacheth unto God, in his <hi>holy Houſe; ai his holy Table,</hi> to ſpeake to God by holy Prayer, to heare him in his holy word, to give him thankes for received bleſſings, for health, food, rayment, manifold preſervations, forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, the hope and expectation of the joyes of heaven, to begge all things requiſit for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21996:35"/>
body or ſoule, to receive the <hi>holy Sacrament</hi> of the body and blood of his bleſſed Saviour thereby to be ſealed to the day of Redemption: Then, as to be ſpecially reverend and devoute in heart within; ſo, to expreſſe the ſame by ſuch behaviour and reſpect without, as may ſhew the reverence and humility ſuitable to, and becomming, the holy ſervant of the holy God, in ſo holy a buſineſſe, in the holy place. And in all this there is no Superſtition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Gods worſhip is to be performed with outward expreſſions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat in the common way of our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary converſation, wee muſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably ſerve God, as well with the members of our bodyes, as with the faculties of our ſoules, None, except peradventure ſome bruitiſh familiſts (a generation given over to a reprobate ſence) will deny. But, I finde it beyond exceptation difficult, to perſwade diverſe men (who yet will ſeeme ſpecially zealous <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. 28.</note> to have God rightly worſhiped) that in Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip there is any uſe of any more then the ſoule or minde alone: And that, becauſe it is ſayd <hi>ſonne, give</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21996:35"/>
                  <hi>me thine heart.</hi> And herein they deale with us, as the Papiſts do in another caſe. For, when we teach that a man is <hi>juſtified by faith in Chriſt.</hi> They preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge us that we exclude workes as not requiſite in a Chriſtian. So, theſe men hearing us urge, that the members of the body muſt be uſed in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, except againſt us; as if we excluded the heart from this duty. But I would gladly requeſt my bretheren to underſtand, that as being <hi>juſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jac.</hi> 2. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>faith,</hi> wee labour <hi>to ſhew our faith by our workes,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to be no true or lively faith, which doth not fructifie and bring forth <hi>good workes:</hi> So by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward geſtures of our bodies, we declare that worſhip which is in the heart, aſſuring our ſelves that there is no devotion in the heart of that man, who maketh no expreſſion thereof, in his outward behaviour. And whereas God ſaith <hi>ſonne, give me thine heart.</hi> I conceive (under correction) that God dealeth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as a tender father, who ſeeing his ſonne plunged into ſome dangerous gulph ſaith <hi>ſonne, give me thine hand,</hi> not that the father intendeth to reskue onely the childes hand: But becauſe, the hand is the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt limbe, for the child to reach out, and for the Father to take hold on, to draw the whole childe out of danger: So almighty God, ſeeing his childe at a lametable paſſe, ready to ſinke to the bottome of hell; ſaith <hi>ſonne give me thy heart.</hi> That ſo God, having gayned hold on the heart, may thereby draw the whole man to eternall ſafety.</p>
               <p>There is ſuch correſpondency, and ſympathy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Soule and the body; as maketh to accord
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21996:36"/>
one with an other, like thoſe Creatures and wheels, mentioned by the Prophet <hi>Ezech. when thoſe went, theſe went; when thoſe ſtoode, theſe ſtoode: when thoſe were lifted up, theſe were lifted up: for, the ſpirit of the living Creatures was in the wheeles.</hi> So, may I well ſay: when the Soule moveth forward in devotion <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eze.</hi> 1. 21.</note> towards God; the body will not be left behinde, but will beare the Soule company. If the Soule in humility be dejected: then the body with a bare head, a bowing waſte and bended knees, is in all geſtures of ſubmiſſion. If the Soule be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated and encouraged by deſire and hope towards God<hi>:</hi> then the eye looketh up, and the hand is lifted up towards heaven, expreſſing outwardly the inward diſpoſition of the Soule. And on the other ſide e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man findeth in his owne experience, that his Soule doth ſympathiſe with the temper of his body. For, if the body be tired with labour, the minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh heavy and dull. And do wee not perceive plainely, that when we betake our ſelves to our knees for prayer; the Soule is humbled within us, by this very geſture? And when when wee lift up our hands and our eyes towards God, wee feele an elevation of the Soule alſo towards the throne of grace.</p>
               <p>There is an inſtance in the booke of Exod. which fully illuſtrateth this point. For when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in fight with <hi>Ameleck, Moſes Aaron, and Hur went up</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 17. 10. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to the tope of the hill. And it came to paſſe when</hi> Moſes <hi>lift up his hand,</hi> Iſrael <hi>prevailed: And when he let downe his hand</hi> Amaleck <hi>prevailed.</hi> Shall we thinke
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21996:36"/>
that there was a charme in this his holding up and letting downe of his hand? Is it not manifeſt, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was heard at his prayers to God, for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? and that, as his handes were borne up, his ſoule did beare up alſo, in the greater meaſure of zeale and faith whereby his prayer became the more <note place="margin">Lyr.</note> powerfull? <hi>per hoc oſtendttur ſuae orationis efficacia. i.</hi> by this is manifeſted the efficacie or force of his prayer. <hi>Nec contra Amalechitas, tantum vis armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. in num. hom.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>quam Moyſis valuit or atio. Vt enim elevaſſet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ad Deum vincibatur Amalech: remiſſae vero &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectae vinci faciebant Iſrael. i.</hi> The force of armes was not ſo powerfull againſt <hi>Ameleck,</hi> as the prayer of <hi>Moſes.</hi> For, as he lifted up his hands, to God, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleck</hi> went by the worſt: but if his hands ſetled or fell downe, <hi>Iſrael</hi> tooke the foyle, St. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the ſame effect. And may we not conceive <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ser. de tom</hi> 93.</note> that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> meaneth the ſame thing, when he will have menat their prayers <hi>to lift up</hi> pure hands? A learned interpreter ſpeaketh full home to this <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8.</note> purpoſe ſaying, upon that text. <hi>Voluit hoc ſymbolo ſignificare vim orationis. Elevatio enim manuum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionem orationis, remiſſio manuum remiſsionem orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis adumbrabat. Elevans manus elevabat &amp; mentem,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cornel. a lap.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; intendebat in Deum: Cum vero laſſus remittebat manus remittebat &amp; orationem. i.</hi> He would by this ſymbol ſet out the force of prayer. For, the lifting up of his hands did ſignifie the earneſtneſſe of his prayer and the ſetling of his hand the ſlaking of his devotion. In lifting up his hand he rowſed up his ſpirit, and dealt with God the more fervenly<hi>:</hi> but
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21996:37"/>
when growen weary he let fall his hand, then he cooled in his prayer.</p>
               <p>As for my part. Whenſoever I ſee any man u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing outward reverence, in the act of Gods worſhip; I ſhall judge him to be the more devoute within, by how much the more he doth outwardly expreſſe, in reverened geſtures: Neither can I ever be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that, that man is inwardly affected with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, towards God: who doth not outwardly declare the ſame, by the reverend behaviour of his <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>a.</hi> 2 <hi>a. q.</hi> 94.</note> body. For as <hi>Aquinas</hi> alleadgeth out of S. <hi>Aug. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior cultus eſt confeſſio quaedam cultus interioris. i.</hi> The outward worſhip is a certeine confeſſion of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip. Wee cannot deny, but that men may make a faire outward ſhew of <hi>holineſſe and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> when they are moſt foul within, through hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and prophaneſſe: as the Phariſies made long prayers, whileſt they intended to devoure wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes houſes. But yet, let me prevent or repreſſe inſolent cenſures, with the words of St. <hi>Paul: Who</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 14. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant?</hi> Thou doſt with thine eyes ſee reverence, in the outward beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour? Thou ſeeſt not what is within, in the heart. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 7.</note> But Chriſtian charity <hi>beleeveth all things and hopeth all things:</hi> and requireth that wee judge the beſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the outward appearance. God only is the judge of the heart, we are to judge according to what wee ſee: and not according to what we ſee not. Wee are taught to be devout and reverend, both within and without<hi>:</hi> And to performe worſhip to God not with the body alone nor with the Soule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alone;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21996:37"/>
but with body and Soule both: that ſo wee may not ſeperate <hi>thoſe, which God hath conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> No doubt, but there is too often an outward ſhew of much devotion and reverence, where there is none or very little within For, impiety can diſſemble. Sathan can change himſelfe into an Angell of light. The woolfe can put on <hi>Sheepes cloathing.</hi> But there can be no inward reverence or devotion in the heart, which doth not ſhew it ſelfe outwardly (except peradventure when ſome perplexing terrour, may for a time make a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man diſcover humane frailety) for, true Religion loveth not to diſſemble. The Angell of light will not transforme himſelfe into a Divell of darkeneſſe: nor will the ſheepe cloath it ſelfe with the ſkinne of a woolfe. And the man which hath a devout and Religious heart, will not ſeeme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, but will declare his piety and probity out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, by the holineſſe of his workes in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and by the reverendneſſe of his behaviour in the worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>The Schoole-men make a threefold act of ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pined in</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 25. <hi>ar.</hi> 2.</note> whereof the firſt is in the underſtanding, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending and conceiving the excellencie of the object, or that which is to be worſhiped. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in the will, inclyning and diſpoſing a man, to honor, that object. And both theſe they call inward worſhip. The third act is the expreſſion of that inward apprehenſion and inclination, by ſenſible ſignes, as, by word, deede, or geſture, and this they call outward worſhip. <hi>Ex duplici natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:21996:38"/>
                  <hi>Compoſiti ſumus intellectuali &amp; ſenſibili. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicem adorationem deo offerimus: Spirituale, qua conſistit in interiori mentis devotione &amp; corporalem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 14. <hi>ar.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>in exteriore corporis humiliatione i.</hi> Wee conſiſt of a two fold nature, intellectuall and ſenſible. Wee performe to God a two fold worſhip: The one Spiritual, conſiſting in the outward devotion, of the minde; and the other corporall, in the outward humiliation of the body.</p>
               <p>But here, my brethen are ready to tell me, that by theſe words of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> what is done by the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> body is but a corporall worſhip: and that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall worſhip conſiſteth in inward devotion, and then they urge the words of our Saviour, ſaying, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſh.</hi> 4. 24. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>God is a ſpirit,</hi> and muſt be worſhipped <hi>in ſpirit and trueth,</hi> whereto they adde the words of St. <hi>Paul: bodily excerciſe profiteth little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be thought, by theſe words, firſt, of Saint <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> that bodily exerciſe doth profit ſome thing: though but a little: and we are not to neglect, much more to abhorre that, which may afford the leaſt furtherance, in the way of Godlyneſſe, and in Gods worſhip. But, if my brethren tell me, that I do much miſtake the meaning of the word, litle in this text: I muſt tell them, that they in thus applying it, to our behaviour in the worſhip of God, do much more miſtake, and fearefully wreſt the words, <hi>bodily exerciſe;</hi> Concerning the meaning whereof, Interpreters do not readily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. But, this I am ſure of; that of all the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters which I have ſeene (and I have purpoſely
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21996:38"/>
made ſome ſearch) not one doth underſtand them of thoſe geſtures of the body in Gods worſhip which we now treate of. And it is manyfeſt that the bodily exerciſes whereof S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, are ſuch as he ſetteth in oppoſition unto true godlines<hi>:</hi> and yet ſuch as, wherein fooliſh people, perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by hypocrites, and guided by idle conceits, and no better then old wives fables, do place Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Abſtinency from <hi>meate and from marriage, v.</hi> 3. unto which we may adde, long and frequent wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, pronouncing of long and many prayers, lying on the cold ground, wearing haire cloth, and the like, with ſuch kind of diſciplining of the body may profit ſomething as they may be uſed. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 26.</note> For, S. <hi>Paul</hi> deemeth thoſe people happy, in regard of the <hi>preſent neceſſity,</hi> which were unmarried. And he alloweth thoſe which are married, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and upon ſome occaſions to withdraw one from an other, that they may the better diſpoſe themſelves to faſting and prayer. Watching faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſuch other chaſtiſings of the body are alſo of profitable uſe, to tame the fleſh, and to bring it into ſubjection to the ſpirit: and ſo to make the whole man the fitter for devotion. But if men place true Godlineſſe, to conſiſt in theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry exerciſes, and ſo conceive with themſelves, that whileſt they performe them, they are <hi>eo nomine,</hi> for that alone, very good people, though otherwiſe they live in the cuſtome and practiſe of foule and known ſinnes: then ſhall they finde that their <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21996:39"/>
                  <hi>exerciſes do profit little:</hi> that is nothing at all, and that in vaine have they wearyed themſelves therein. And ſo; if a man thinke that though he neglect the true duties of godlineſſe; he is yet a godly man; becauſe he is very exact in all the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of outward reverence in Gods worſhip: I paralell that man with an other ſect of hypocrites, whoſe whole godlineſſe conſiſteth, in going to to ſome ſelected Church, and in being preſent where a Sermon is: though in the meane time, they learne nothing and practice as little of any true godlineſſe. Both theſe ſorts of men I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be an hypocriticall and ſuperſtitious generation both a like. And of them both I ſay that <hi>they have a forme of Godlines: but deny the power thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though then <hi>bodily exerciſes</hi> profit not thoſe, who place their whole Religion and goodneſſe in them, as they are meer bodily actes. Yet are they not unprofitable for Chriſtian men, who make the right uſe of them, either to tame <hi>the body</hi> and to <hi>bring it into ſubjection,</hi> by faſting, ſack cloth and aſhes and the like: or to make outward expreſſion of inward devotion: as by bending the knee, bowing the body, lifting up the hands and eyes and ſuch like geſtures in Gods worſhip.</p>
               <p>As for the wordes of our bleſſed Saviour: <hi>God is a ſpirit, and muſt be worſhipped in ſpirit and in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 95. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>trutb.</hi> I aſke thoſe men, which alledge them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt outward reverence; what they will ſay to holy and devoute <hi>David</hi> when he ſaith: <hi>O come</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21996:39"/>
                  <hi>let us worſhip and fall downe and kneele before the Lord our maker?</hi> Doth not the ſpirit of God here require the geſtures, of bowing downe and knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be uſed in Gods worſhip?</p>
               <p>But for further ſatisfaction herein we will ſpend a few lines (though one would thinke words need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in ſo cleare a caſe) in the expoſition of our Saviours wordes. Wee therefore give our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to underſtand, that the word <hi>Spirit</hi> in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath divers ſinifications, as <hi>i.</hi> The regenerate man is called the <hi>Spirit.</hi> Matth. 26. 41. <hi>The Spirit is willing the fleſh is weak</hi> 2 The will or inclination. 2 Cron. 36. 22. <hi>The Lord ſtirred up the Spirit of Cyrus.</hi> 3 The courage of a man. Joſh. 5. 1. <hi>There was no ſpirit in them any more becauſe of the children of Iſrael,</hi> 4 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and knowledge</hi> Dan. 5. 12. <hi>An excellent Spirit and underſtanding and knowlegde were found in</hi> Daniell. 5 <hi>Doctrine or teaching</hi> 1 Joh. 4. 1. <hi>Beleeve not every Spirit but try the Spirits.</hi> So then, take the word <hi>Spirit</hi> in any of theſe ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and it will nothing hinder the uſe of corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or bodily geſtures in the worſhip of God. For, to worſhip God in <hi>Spirit,</hi> is to worſhip him with a regenerate or new man which after <hi>God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holyneſſe</hi> Eph. 4. 24. It is no compaſſing of Gods Altar, without <hi>hands waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Innocency</hi> Pſ. 26. 6. no praying to God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pure handes lifted up. 1 Tim. 8. No com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the marriage feaſt <hi>without a wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Mat. 22. So, it is not for any to performe the holy act of worſhip, to the holy God, that is
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21996:40"/>
not regenerate and holy and will ſo worſhip <hi>in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and truth</hi> i. in true holineſſe. For, God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>ſuch to worſhip him.</hi> 2. <hi>God muſt be worſhiped in Spirit.</hi> i. with a willing ready and chearefull mind <hi>Deborah</hi> in her ſong <hi>Iudic.</hi> 5. 2. doth prayſe God for the people <hi>that became ſo willing.</hi> And 1 Pet. 5. 2. Gods flock muſt be fed, not by <hi>conſtraint but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly</hi> and ſo, Gods worſhip muſt be performed in Spirit, that is, <hi>willingly.</hi> 3. <hi>God muſt be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped in ſpirit.</hi> i. Not faintly and droopingly<hi>:</hi> but couragiouſly and zealouſly in <hi>the fervency of the ſpirit</hi> as Rom. 10, 11. 5 <hi>God muſt be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſpirit and in truth.</hi> i. with underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and knowledge, rightly informed. Laſtly<hi>: God must be worſhiped in ſpirit and truth.</hi> i. Guided by the holy ſpirit of God<hi>:</hi> as all the ſonnes of God are led by the ſpirit. Rom. 8. 14. which <hi>leadeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth.</hi> Joh. 16. 13. And this is home to the text <hi>in ſpirit and truth;</hi> when in Gods worſhip we ſo make uſe of either body or ſoule as by Gods word and ſpirit, wee are thereto directed. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall actes may be done in the Spirit as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours going up to the mount. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. was a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall act, and yet it was done in the Spirit: For, <hi>he was led by the Spirit</hi> v. 1. And to this effect are the words of the Schoole-man cleare and full, in in the place before alledged, <hi>Adoratio Corporalis in Spiritu fit, in quantum ex ſpirituali devotione pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit, &amp; ad eam ordinatur.</hi> i. Bodily worſhip is <note place="margin">2. 2. <hi>q</hi> 84. <hi>ar. i</hi>
                  </note> done in the ſpirit, in as much as it proceedeth from ſpirituall devotion, and is made to ſerve thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21996:40"/>
When our brethren Pray or Preach, do they not uſe a bodily member, <hi>viz.</hi> the toung, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe themſelves withall? The uſing of the tounge is a <hi>bodily exerciſe,</hi> as well as the bowing of the knee. And yet, I hope, they thinke that they do both Preach and Pray in the ſpirit. Are not eating and drinking bodily actions? And yet I truſt wee do eate and drinke in the ſpirit: when wee do it in the feare of God, and (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth) to <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods glory.</hi> Wee read in Rev. 4. v. 10. of foure and twenty Elders, who <hi>fell downe on their faces &amp; worſhipped him, who liveth for ever.</hi> Shall wee ſay that they woſhiped not in <hi>Spirit and truth,</hi> becauſe they uſed a geſture of humilitie and reverence in falling downe <hi>upon their faces?</hi> It is lamentable to behold men pretending ſincerity and love of trueth, thus perverſly wringing Gods holy word and willfully ſhutting their eyes, againſt ſo cleare light of ſo manifeſt a truth.</p>
               <p>When the knee is bent, the body bowed or the hand lifted up devoutly unto God<hi>:</hi> theſe are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede <hi>bodily exerciſes</hi> or actes done by the members of the body, as outward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of inward devotion: but no acts of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21996:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>The ſeverall geſtures uſed by Gods Servants in his worſhip are all free from Superſtition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE have hitherto made ſcearch, in and about the houſe of God, or place of Chriſtian aſſembly, wee have carefully pryed into every nooke and corner thereof, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Servants of God, performing worſhip unto God, ſo as their inward devotions are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and expreſſed by their outward geſtures and demeanures; God being ſo worſhipped by their whole man, body and Soule. But in all this wee have found <hi>no Superſtition.</hi> But <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>all things decently and in good order.</hi> Come we now and examin thoſe outward demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures, geſtures and expreſſions, ſeverally and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly: And all that wee do in our Churches in their diſtinct formes and poſtures: leaſt yet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any of them, ſome peece of ſuperſtition be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure concealed, and here I muſt confeſſe, ſome evill <hi>Surmiſers</hi> have unjuſtly cauſed much ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition: For, our juſtification therefore and the manifeſting of truth to Gods glory, <hi>Come and ſee all</hi> that is done in our Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21996:41"/>
Wee confeſſe our ſinnes unto God. Wee begge pardon at the hands of God. Wee give God thanks for what wee have received<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wee crave from God what wee ſtand in need of. Wee remember the afflictions of all diſtreſſed people, with our prayers for them all, and our almes to the poorer ſort. We reade, and heare read, the holy Bible and godly expoſitions, homilyes and ſermons, whereby the ignorant are inſtructed, the unruly admoniſhed, the backward exhorted, the hard-hearted terrefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the feeble encouraged the aflicted conſcience comforted. We adminiſter the Sacraments of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the Lords ſupper. Is any of theſe any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious act? Our ſcrupulous brethren allow all this. But then thus they take exception.</p>
               <p>In your very entrance into the Church, you <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> put off your hats and kneele downe and pray: as if either God were not in other places: or, that wee might not pray, but in the Church.</p>
               <p>If we taught men, that they ought not to pray <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> anywhere elſe, but in a Church, or place conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated: or that we did not uſe to pray in any other place: then, there were ſome cauſe to object thus againſt us. But we are in our Churches, from time to time called upon, to <hi>pray continually, and in all things to give thankes.</hi> Is it not thus extant in our booke of common prayer? <hi>It is very meete right and our bounden duty, that we ſhould at all times and in all places give thankes to thee O holy father, Lord of heaven and earth.</hi> Is there not in that booke ſpeciall ſervice to be uſed in privat houſes, at the bed ſide of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21996:42"/>
ſick people? Is not the booke it ſelfe free and vendible, by every Stationer, not only for the publick worſhip in Churches: but alſo for the uſe of every private man in his own houſe? Be there not alſo plenty of other bookes in print, of formes of prayers to be made unto God, upon ſeverall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions at any time, in any place, by any man, whoſe ſoule is poſſeſſed with ſo good devotion? And therfore it is plaine, that our devotion and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline doth not therfore encline us to pray, when we come within a Church; as if we held that the only place, where a man may pray: but for that the Church is an houſe of prayer (as we have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhewed) this very place putteth a man in mind, and calleth upon him, there ſpecially, to pray: in ſomuch that it is a place purpoſely ſet apart, for that very end and purpoſe: that whatſoever a man doth elſewhere, yet here he ſhould pray becauſe this is the houſe of prayer. We uncover our heads in the Church: as in the preſence Chamber on earth, of the King of heaven and earth. And when we pray, we kneele, becauſe kneeling is the geſture of humility, becomming a man who preferreth his petition, to the God of heaven.</p>
               <p>In the fourth Century, a time abounding with prodigious haereſies, aroſe one <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> who, among others of his prophane opinions, wherwith many became infected, maintained: that Churches <note place="margin">Concil. Gangr.</note> and meetings therein are to be deſpiſed. <hi>Damaſcus</hi> and Saint <hi>Auguſtin</hi> mention this to have been the haereſie of the Meſſalini otherwiſe called <hi>Euchites</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:21996:42"/>
and <hi>Enthuſiaſtes,</hi> who alſo had ſo meane an opinion of Baptiſme and the Lords ſupper, as that they held <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan. de haeres.</hi> 8 <hi>Aug. Serm. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Arrianos. l.</hi> 4. <hi>C.</hi> 11. <hi>de ecliis. c.</hi> 37.</note> them altogether uneffectuall and unprofitable<hi>:</hi> as <hi>Theodoret</hi> reporteth. <hi>Turrecremata</hi> telleth us, that the fratricellian haeritiques <hi>a moſt impure ſect,</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained among other things, <hi>Eccelſiam non plus va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere ad orandum: quam porcorum ſtabulum. i.</hi> That the Church avayleth a man for prayer, no more then a ſwine-ſty. O my brethren, conforme not yourſelves to the abominable fancies of theſe filthie dreamers, odious to God, and in the judgment of the Church damned haeretiques.</p>
               <p>To pray, is no ſuperſtitius act. To pray knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is no ſuperſtition. To pray in a Church, as we ſhewed cap. 4. is no ſuperſtition. To uſe reverend geſtures and behaviour of humility, in the preſence of God, is no ſuperſtition. To repute the Church to be Gods houſe is no ſuperſtition, Therefore, for a man entring into a Church to put off his hat, and being come in, to kneele downe and to pray to God: are no ſuperſtition but pious acts of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian devotion.</p>
               <p>You have ſo many ſeverall geſtures and poſtures; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> ſometimes ſitting; ſometimes kneeling; ſometimes ſtanding; ſometimes bowing. Why may not men uſe what geſtures they pleaſe: ſo that the heart be right?</p>
               <p>I have already ſhewed that a reverend heart can <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> not but produce reverend demeanure in Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And yet further to anſwer this cavill, I ſay. It is not inough, that our geſtures be reverend and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21996:43"/>
ſober, in the generall, except alſo they be ſuteable and fit to expreſſe the preſent act, whereto they are applyed. And firſt, for ſitting. If humane frailty ſpecially in aged people, could endure it) ſitting would not at all be uſed in the houſe of God; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially during the holy buſineſſe of Gods ſervice. But in conſideration of the infirmity of fleſh and blood, Reſt is ſometimes requiſite: leaſt too much weakeneſſe either diminiſh or diſturb devotion. Therefore, the indulgence of the Church permitteth us, to ſit whileſt the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is reading or expounding any part of the word of God for our inſtruction: and while doctrines are taught and applyed for our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther edification. But when we come to utter an hymne or petition, then the miniſter, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpake unto the people, doth now joyn with the people: and both miniſter and people, with one heart and voice, joyn in a language to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. And therefore, compoſe themſelves to a geſture of ſolemne adoration and worſhip: which I never knew ſitting to be: neither do I thnike that any preſident can be found in all the whole Bible, of any, either Congregations aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled or perſons in privat, ſitting at their ſolemn worſhip of almighty God. We find in the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 4. 2.</note> God deſcribed upon his throne: and foure and twenty Elders, wearing crownes, ſitting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo many ſeates, round about the throne. And anon, thoſe Elders betake themſelves to <hi>worſhip him that ſitteth on the throne.</hi> But now they keepe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21996:43"/>
themſelves no longer on their ſeates: when they are to performe the act of ſolemne worſhip. But <hi>they fall downe before him that ſate on the throne, and caſt their crownes before the throne</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou art worthy O Lord to receive glory &amp;c.</hi> So alſo cap. 11. ver. 16. there are 24 Elders, <hi>who ſit before God, on their ſeates.</hi> But when they worſhip they <hi>fall downe on their faces.</hi> We read alſo of ſome that worſhipped God ſtanding. So did the publican <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtanding a far off, he ſaid: <hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> And a great company whom no man could number, <hi>did ſtand before the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 18. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>throne, in the ſight of the Lambe and cryed with a loud</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>voice ſaying: Salvation from our God which ſitteth on the throne.</hi> And therefore we give <hi>glory to the father ſonne and holy Ghoſt:</hi> or recite ſome <hi>hymne, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by the Church to be pronounced by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and people joyntly, to glorifie and praiſe God withall <hi>ſtanding;</hi> both in imitation of theſe examples, and alſo accompting it the more reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend geſture then ſitting (which we never finde uſed in the ſolemne and publique worſhip by Gods people. And in all this no man can point out any Superſtition.</p>
               <p>Againe, we uſe the geſture of ſtanding, when wee publiquely rehearſe the articles of our faith, or attend unto thoſe choiſe portions of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, appointed for their ſpeciall times and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. And both theſe are the ſame: For, the Creede is the breviate of the Goſpell, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell is in the Creede or the articles of our Faith at
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21996:44"/>
large. At the rehearſing of the one, and at the reading of the other, we ſtand up. The reaſon is, to ſignifie and expreſſe hereby our reſolution and readyneſſe to ſtand, and perſevere to the end, in this Faith, which we do profeſſe. And this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is according to ſcripture: which by the metaphor of <hi>ſtanding</hi> ſetteth out Chriſtian forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and perſeverance as Rom. 5. 2. <hi>we are by faitb admitted to this grace wherein we ſtand.</hi> And cap. 11. 20. <hi>Thou ſtandeſt by faith.</hi> So 1 Cor. 16. 13. <hi>Stande in the faith.</hi> And 1 Pet. 5. 12. <hi>This is the grace wherein yee ſtand.</hi> So then, we by this geſture of <hi>ſtanding</hi> at the Creede or Goſpell, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our conſtancy or perſeverance.</p>
               <p>But when the ſcripture ſpeaketh of ſtanding in <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> grace or in the faith, it doth not intend a bodily but a <hi>ſpirituall ſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is very true. And when wee by our bodily ſtanding do profeſſe our ſpirituall ſtanding, we do <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> herein no whit ſwarve from the meaning of the Scripture: But what the Scripture expreſſeth in word, we declare by a geſture, of the ſame ſignification. And ſo, in this is no ſuperſtition.</p>
               <p>One would think that no body ſhould be ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, as to diſlike the geſture of kneeling in prayer. But becauſe I have ſeene with mine eyes, and that not ſeldome, whole troops of men and women, and thoſe not of the meaneſt, in the time and place of divine Service, while prayers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations were made unto God, ſit all the while. I think not altogether needleſſe, to free the geſture
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21996:44"/>
of kneeling in Gods worſhip, from all ſuſpition of ſuperſtition. And that by precept, practiſe and reaſon, For precept take the words of the Pſalmiſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 95. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>O come, let us worſhip and fall downe, and kneele, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord our maker.</hi> For practice we will looke upon the fareſt preſident. Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt kneeled downe and prayed.</hi> If <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. 41.</note> men will be ruled by reaſon, they will not, when they are to petition the King, of Kings, omit ſuch a geſture of humility, as kneeling is, being the moſt ſuitable for a man at his prayers, and for this cauſe we kneele at the holy Communion recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; whereat, we both lift up thankfull hearts unto God, for the death and reſurection of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> as alſo beg of God, that by the merits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>our bodies and Soules may be preſerved to everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life?</hi> It is not denyed, but that a man may pray ſitting, walking, ſtanding or layd along: For we ought to pray <hi>alwayes.</hi> But when a man beta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe to a ſet exerciſe of prayer, and that ſpecially, in the publique Congregation, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is the fitteſt, and no Superſtitious ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
               <p>But, though divers things in uſe with you in <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> your worſhip, might in themſelves be ſomething indifferent and tollerable, yet there are ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures uſed in your Churches, very offenſive to weake Conſciences and therefore ought to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.</p>
               <p>How weake the conſciences of theſe men be, I muſt leave it to God to judge of. But I muſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21996:45"/>
needes thinke that their fancies are ſtrong whileſt they will not beleeve, but that they have better knowledge then their teachers, and more wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then their Governors. For, they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, what the miniſter muſt teach, and how, both Church and Common-wealth muſt be orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And wherein their Miniſters teach, or their Governours Command, otherwiſe then they like of, they will ſlight the one, and diſobey the other. But, to come to the point. What is that, which is ſo offenſive above the reſt. Let it come forth: and ſhewe its Superſtitious face<hi>:</hi> that when wee ſee it to be ſuch wee may abhor it thereafter. It is, as I am told (for elſe I ſhould never have magnified it) The bowing which wee uſe at the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and at the Communion Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>For, as the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the plaine text telleth me: <hi>that every knee ſhall bow thereat.</hi> But forward people thinke to evade the authority of this text, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 10.</note> by ſaying, that the word <hi>Name</hi> doth in ſcripture ſometimes ſignifie power. And this wee deny not: and wee acknowledge further, that it alſo ſignifieth divers other things, as, fame or renoune 2 Cro. 26. 8. <hi>His name went forth to the entrance of Aegypt.</hi> So it ſignifieth alſo Poſterity Deut. 25 7. <hi>My husbands brother refuſeth to raiſe up a name unto his brother.</hi> It is taken for memory or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Eſ. 56. 5. <hi>God will give the eunuches in his houſe a name.</hi> But now what of all this? will they ſay that the reverence mentioned in the text
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21996:45"/>
Philip. 2. is to be given peradventure to the power, renown or memory of the ſonne of God<hi>:</hi> and not to be done, when wee heare him named by the name JESUS? But then, here would I know of them, which of theſe, <hi>power renowne or memory,</hi> ſhall I conceive to be meant in this text by the word <hi>Name?</hi> If they ſay, his power, then I aſke why not his renowne? If they ſay his renowne, then why, not his memoriall? For, the word <hi>Name</hi> doth in Scripture, by a trope, ſignifie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of theſe. And when we leave the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſence of any word in Scripture, wee muſt ſhew ſome neceſſity why we do ſo, and make it plaine, that it muſt be taken in that ſignificative ſence, which we give therof. It is not inough to ſay, ſuch <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De doct. Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 3 <hi>C.</hi> 10.</note> a word is in ſome places taken in a figurative ſence and therefore I will ſo underſtand it here, and where I liſt beſides. St <hi>Auſtine,</hi> dealing with ſuch looſe expounders of Scripture, ſaith <hi>Nihil facilius eſt quam dicere Tropus eſt: figura eſt, modus quidam dicendi eſt, Hebraiſmus eſt. i.</hi> It is an eaſie matter to ſay, it is a Trope: It is a figure: It is a certaine forme of ſpeech: It is an Hebraiſme. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he giveth this rule. <hi>Oratio figurata eſt; quae proprieintellecta, nec ad fidem nec ad dilectionem nec ad ullam aedificationem acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modari poteſt. i.</hi> Then is the ſpeech figurative, when it cannot be made to ſerve, for either faith or charity or any edification, in the proper ſence of the words. <hi>Illy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cus,</hi> that one of the centuriſtes, well knowne to be no friend to Superſtition doth among the reſt of his rules,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21996:46"/>
for the right underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of ſcripture, give this for <note place="margin">De rat. Cogn. Sacr. lit.</note> one. <hi>Verba ſacraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> literaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proprie acccipienda ſunt, niſi loci ſenſus in alique<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fidei articulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. i.</hi> The words of holy Scripture are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in their proper ſence: ecept that ſo, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the words do directy fal foul upon ſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith. And in an other place he thus advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. <hi>Ne quaerat aliquis umbras aut ſectetur ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia allegorianum, niſi manifeſta ſit allegoria; &amp; lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſus ſit alioquin inutilis aut abſurdus. i.</hi> let not a man hunt after ſhadows or dreame of allegories, except there be a manifeſt allegory: And that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an allegory, the literall ſenſe be unprofitable and abſurd. And to this point a learned Countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of our own ſpeaketh home, ſaying <hi>Allegoryes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perk. in. gal.</hi> 4. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>are to be admitted, when the words ſound againſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon, analogy of faith or good manners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us conſider theſe rules, and ſee, if there be any neceſſity that the word <hi>Name,</hi> in the text to the Philipians, be underſtood in any other then the proper ſenſe. Is it againſt common reaſon, Faith, Charity or good manners, ſo to underſtand it? Or is it againſt the ſcope of that place, or of any other part or peece of ſcripture; for me to bow my knee, or to expreſſe reverence, by any ſeemly outward geſture, when I heare my bleſſed Lord and Saviour named, by his proper name, JESUS? How then dare I ſuffer my fancy, here to leave the prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aſe, and to deviſe a figure: as if I might worke the Scripture, like a noſe of waxe, as I liſt my ſelf? I will here adde one rule more which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21996:46"/>
we have from Saint <hi>Hillary. Optimus lector eſt, qui dictorum intelligentiam expectat ex dictis, potius quam imponat, et retulerit potius quam attulerit: Neque cogat id videri dictis contineri, quod ante le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem praeſumpſerit intelligendum.</hi> i. He is the beſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>l. de trin.</hi> 1.</note> reader of Scriptures, who lookes for the meaning of the words in the words, rather then putteth or impoſeth a meaning upon them: who fetcheth the ſenſe from the words, rather then bringeth it unto them. And who enforceth not that to ſeem to be contained in them, which he preſumed to find there before he read them.</p>
               <p>If any man will contend that yet there is an alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> in that text, becauſe <hi>knees</hi> are there aſcribed to <hi>things in heaven and things in earth and things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth.</hi> I anſwer, that when knees are aſcribed <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> to things which properly have none, there, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity enforceth us to acknowledge a figure. But the Son of, God our bleſſed Saviour hath a name, even the name JESUS, in the proper ſenſe. And men have knees, not figuratively, but properly. Therefore it is without any figure, to ſay, that men having knees naturally, ſhall bow thoſe knees at the name JESUS, which is not a metaphorical but the proper name of the Son of God. And ſo there is no neceſſity to ſeeke a figure in that text in the word <hi>name,</hi> or in the word <hi>knees,</hi> ſo farre as the duty concerneth man. But it is very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, againſt the faith of a good Conſcience, and againſt the true rules of right interpreting the Scriptures, thus to rove at figures and to imagine
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21996:47"/>
allegories where we need not: and upon bare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine conjectures, not knowing certainly, what to ſtand unto.</p>
               <p>But by this bowing at the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> we ſhall <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> magnifie the <hi>Son</hi> above the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No ſuch matter; but we ſhall honour the <hi>Father</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> in the <hi>Son:</hi> For ſo ſaith the text, that this is done <hi>to the glory of God the Father.</hi> And ſeeing no man can ſay that <hi>Jeſus is the Lord: but by the holy Ghoſt:</hi> Let us never feare, that, that reſpect which we do to our Saviour, by the inſtinct and direction of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> can be any diminution or diſparagement to the holy <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> Will any man ſay, that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> did diſparage either the Father or the holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> when ſhe ſaid: <hi>My ſpirit rejoiceth in God my Saviour?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 47.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But why then is this reverence done at the name <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> of the ſecond perſon, more then at the name of the firſt or third? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe that, not the <hi>Father</hi> nor the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> but the <hi>Son made himſelfe of no reputation and tooke upon him the ſhape of a ſervant and became obedient to the death, even the death of the Croſſe; therefore God hath exalted Him and given Him a name above every</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>name that at the name of Jeſus every Knee ſhould bow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall I reverence a word or bow to a ſound of letters? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>We bow to and worſhip, not the word, ſound <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> or letters: but God, thereby expreſſed. The word is our Remembrancer, to put us in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21996:47"/>
minde of the duty which we owe to <hi>God</hi> our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why is this ſpeciall reverence done at this, more then at any other name of God? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Every name of God is reverend and holy. But whereas a ſinfull man ſhall find terror, in other <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> names of God, expreſſing his Majeſty, Power, Juſtice and the like: This is the only name of God which fully ſetteth out unto us the mercy of God to eternall ſalvation. For, therefore is he called <hi>Jeſus, becauſe he ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi> And, <hi>there is no other name under heaven given,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>Luc.</hi> 4. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> For ſo much therefore, as in this name we find the greateſt, yea unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Comfort: It is agreeable to good reaſon, that we be by this name ſtirred up and affected with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable joy within: and that we make expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, to the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> by devout out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reverence.</p>
               <p>I would, my brethren which are ſo ſcrupulous in this point, would, without prejudice, read the learned and cleare tteatiſes, which are extant on this argument: and ſpecially that exquiſite peece of that moſt learned and judicious Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> And that, (ſetting aſide their cauſeleſſe quarrell, againſt his being Lord Biſhop) they would weigh his reaſons with an humble ſpirit, and an heart lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 13.</note> up to God, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to be guided by that Spirit of truth, which our Saviour promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſend, <hi>to guide us all, into all truth.</hi> Then I make no doubt, but they would ſoone ſee, that in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21996:48"/>
bowing the knee to God, at the mention of the name of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> there is no Superſtition.</p>
               <p>But you call the Communion table an altar: and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> you adore it, by bowing and doing reverence thereunto.</p>
               <p>We are not by any Canon or rule (that I know) required, to call it an altar. And the now Lord <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> Biſhop of <hi>Elie</hi> (a man ſpecially zealous to reſtore Gods publique worſhip to the primitive luſtre) in the articles which he lately exhibited, in his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, when he was Biſhop of Norwich, doth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ. Nyſſen.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> not at all call it by the name <hi>altar,</hi> but ſometime the Communion table; and ſometime in the words of the Fathers <hi>the holy Table.</hi> And yet, it hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently been called indifferently, by either name, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coale from the Altar. Altar. Chriſtianum.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Antid. Lincol.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Altar</hi> or <hi>Table:</hi> and may indifferently beare either name: as is abundantly cleared of late, by divers learned pennes; who have eaſed me, from any la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in this point: and are ſufficient to ſatiſfie any reaſonable ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Neither know I any particular or oppoſitive law enjoyning us, to bow at the <hi>altar</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion table.</hi> Yet the devotion of thoſe which do practice it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grounded upon the cuſtome of the Catholick Church of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> is (in my poore judgment) not only juſtifiable but alſo commendable. For what is there to be ſaid againſt it?</p>
               <p>It is ſuperſtition, in Gods worſhip, to bow or do <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> reverence to any creature.</p>
               <p>Wee do not bow, to the table: but, at the table <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> as a man in his onw houſe praying, either in his clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21996:48"/>
by himſelfe or in ſome roome amongſt his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, kneeleth at his chaire or table is not ſayd to kneele to his ſtoole or table. So, we, that bow at the Communion table, do our reverence there, not to the table, but to God, at the table.</p>
               <p>And why there more then any where elſe? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer firſt, by ſuch another queſtion. Why <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> not there as well as any where elſe? what is there to forbid me to do my duty reverently unto God in that place? Againe I aſke my brother, why was <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 5 at the fire buſh <hi>to put his ſhooes from his feet,</hi> rather there, then in any other place? I hope he will anſwer me with Gods own reaſon and words <hi>viz. becauſe the place</hi> was <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ground.</hi> Then I aſk once more; what made that place holyer then an other? will it not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be, Gods ſpeciall preſence, there ſpecially manifeſted in the voice that ſpake and the fire which burned not the buſh? All this is cleare and undeniable. And from hence then, thus it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth neceſſarily <hi>A place, where God by ſpeciall ſignes manifeſteth his ſpeciall preſence, is more holy then another place.</hi> (though not in nature, yet in uſe and relation) <hi>And there, men are to demeane them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with ſpecial reverence therefore.</hi> But the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion table is a place, where God manifeſteth himſelfe, ſpecially preſent, in the Sacrament of the body and blood of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And therefore men ought there to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane themſelves with ſpeciall reverence, towards God, there ſpecially preſent. For, when a man
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21996:49"/>
conſidereth <hi>the love of God in Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſealed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, by the body and blood of Chriſt, whereof the Communion table doth ſpecially put him in minde, as being a table ſpecially ſet up, and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, for that banquet; then the heart (if it be right) is lifted up in reverend thankefullneſſe to our mercifull God: and the body boweth, to expreſſe that reverence and thankfulneſſe, which the heart conceiveth.</p>
               <p>If the Sacrament were alwayes on the table, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> then, this argument might have ſome ſhew of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but we ſee men bow, when nothing is on the table.</p>
               <p>The Communion table, being, appropriated for the Service of the Communion retaineth ſtill <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ </seg>
                  </label> its relation to that Sacrament, and ſtill calleth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, to remember the love of God to us, in the <hi>body and blood of Chriſt:</hi> and therefore, to be reverently thankfull. And ſo it continueth ſtill an <hi>holy Table:</hi> in the regard of the holy things, which belong unto it, though they be not really preſent upon it.</p>
               <p>If this matter of permanent relation, ſeemeth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.</note> harſh to any: let him conſider a paſſage in the book of Gen. where the caſe is thus: God in a dreame exhibiteth unto <hi>Jacob</hi> ſpeciall ſignes of his ſpeciall preſence, in that place where <hi>Jacob</hi> was then ſleeping. In the morning <hi>Jacob</hi> awaketh. But then, there appeareth not any of thoſe ſignes. And yet, in relation to that preſence of God, which had in the night before appeared unto him, in thoſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21996:49"/>
ſignes he ſaith: <hi>O how dreadfull is</hi> (not was) <hi>this place It is (not was) the houſe of God.</hi> Is the place now the houſe of God, and a place to affect <hi>Jacob</hi> with dread, though the ſignes be not preſent, upon the place? And ſhall not the Communion table be ſtil the table of God, and an holy Table to affect us with reverence, though the ſacrament be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes actually on the table? Did not our Saviour call the Temple an <hi>houſe of Prayer,</hi> and not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it to be at all an houſe of Merchandiſe? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might it ſerve the turne of the money chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to ſave them from the whip, to have ſaid: wee will not trade in the Temple, in the time of Sacrifice or of Prayer or of Preaching; but only, when the Service is ended. For, the Temple is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes an <hi>houſe of prayer:</hi> whether men be there at <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. 21.</note> Praiers, or not. And ſo the holy Table is alwaies <hi>the Communion Table, or Table of the Lord:</hi> whether the Sacrament be upon it or not. Doth not our Saviour alſo tell us, that <hi>he which ſweareth by the Temple, ſweareth by him that dwelleth in the Temple?</hi> The Temple was ordeined for the worſhip of God<hi>:</hi> And therefore God dwelled in the Temple in ſpeciall manner- <hi>Idcirco jurans per templum ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratper</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lyr.</note> 
                  <hi>Deum qui colitur in Templo. i.</hi> For that very cauſe, he that ſweareth by the Temple ſweareth by God which is worſhiped in the Temple. Will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body now be ſo idle as to ſay, that this rule doth hold, if a man ſweare juſt then, when they are at Prayer, or at Sacrifice in the Temple, and not elſe<hi>:</hi> but that a man ſwearing by the Temple, when the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21996:50"/>
Service is done, doth not ſweare by God? Is it not alſo in the ſame Chapter ſayd, by the ſame ſacred mouth that <hi>he which ſweareth by the Altar, ſweareth by it, and by all that is upon it?</hi> Should he not now ſhew himſelfe ſenceles, who ſhould ſay, that this rule holdeth only ſo longe as there is any Sacrifice or Oblation on the Altar and no longer? This were right to follow the prophane ſence of ſtrang people in this age, who inmitate or comply with the filthy Fratricellians, before mentioned, which allow no difference, betweene a Church and a Barne, when Service is ended: or betweene the Communion Table, and thier own common ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when the adminiſtration of the ſacrament is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. But know we, who in duty and humility ſubmit our ſelves, to be taught by God, in his holy word; that as between God and the Temple, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Oblation and the Altar, in the old Teſtament: ſo now between God and the Church, between the Communion table &amp; the <hi>body</hi> &amp; <hi>blood of Chriſt under the Goſpell:</hi> the relation doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. So that, whenſoever the holy table com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into our eyes, it ought to put us in minde, of the mercy of God, in the blood and merit of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> And ſhall not then this object beget thankfullneſſe and reverence in my heart? Or may not that reverence which is conceived in mine heart be expreſſed in the geſtures of my body? we do reverence at our entrance into the Kings Chamber of preſence, and al the while we are there, and ſpecially when we come neere the chaire of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21996:50"/>
ſtate: though his Majeſty be not there in perſon. And our brethren do not call this Superſtition. But let them then tell me. Should we not much more do ſo, when we come into the Church, which is the preſence of God; and while we are there, and ſpecially when we approach the holy Table? But they tell us, that it is not the like reaſon; becauſe the one is Civill and the other a Religious reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Whereas, if their reaſon could reach it: or if their frowardneſſe would acknowledge it, the reaſon or argument is moſt ſtrong, and drawne <hi>à minori ad majus,</hi> from the leſſer to the greater thus: If we reverence a King, who is a mortall man, at the ſimboles of his Majeſty: and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials of his Soveraignity: how much more the God of heaven, in our entrance into his houſe and drawing neere his holy Table? Neither let them flatter themſelves with the miſſeunderſtood and miſſeapplyed diſtinction of Religious and Civill reverence: When Religion doth not leſſe bind us to reverence God, with our whol man, body and ſoule, then civility doth oblige us to reſpect man: neither doth religion bar but regulate actions and matters of civility. Therefore, by how much more God is greater then man, and the Soveraigne more to be honoured then his Deputy: we are to be more reverent in the Church, then in the Kings Chamber of preſence, and at the Communion Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then at the chaire of State. If we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence the King not with the body alone but alſo with the heart, ſo are we to reverence God, not
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21996:51"/>
only with the heart: but alſo with the body. And ſo God in the King, and the King for God, with the whol man. So that this very geſture of bowing at the Communion Table rightly performed is not at all any Superſtition but rather a Chriſtian duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>They who unjuſtly charge us with Superſtition, are themſelves moſt Superſtitious.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE have made ſearch in the tents of <hi>Jacob Leah,</hi> and the handmaydes, narrowly: but but have not found yet any of <hi>Labans</hi> Idols: That is we have conſidered, the Cathedrall and and parochian Churches, and taken notice of every corner, and of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular thing and geſture done and uſed in the ſame. But God be thanked we have not in any of them found any Superſtition. And therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently returne <hi>à non eſt inventus.</hi> i. There is no <hi>Superſtition found in all our Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come we now then, into the Tent of <hi>Rachell.</hi> I mean the ſociety of thoſe, who challenge us of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:21996:51"/>
I hope, it wil not offend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we give them the name of <hi>Rachell.</hi> For, as ſhe was the fayreſt of al the wives of <hi>Jacob:</hi> ſo theſe men conceive them ſelves to be, the pureſt and ſincereſt, &amp; ſo, the fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt worſhippers of all the reſt. But we no ſooner come into her tent, but that we find her verbally very reſpective of her Father: Yet really and in deed, very undutifull and hypocriticall. <hi>Let it</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>not diſpleaſe my Lord, that I can not riſe; For the cuſtome of women is upon me. Let it not diſpleaſe,</hi> is very ſmooth language. The terme, <hi>Lord,</hi> as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was a word of reverence in the mouth of <hi>Sarah</hi> to her huſband: ſo, it ſeemeth a little of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from the tounge of <hi>Rachell</hi> to her Father: But the playne truth is, that it is not the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of her Father, but the retaining of her Idolls and perſevering in her <hi>Superſtition,</hi> that ſhe regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. Nor is ſhe aſhamed to tell her Father, <hi>I can not riſe.</hi> And leaſt ſhe might be ſuſpected to ſpeak falſly (as ſhe did) ſhee hath like a cunning diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, quickly found a faire Cloake, to palliate her iniquity, and to make her lye to ſeeme a truth. <hi>The Cuſtome of women is upon her. Fallitur pater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento muliebri ac honeſtiſſima ratione ac ſpecie delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur.</hi> The Father is deluded with a tricke of a <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans wit,</hi> and beguiled with a faire pretence and ſemblance. I am not very willing to faſten theſe conditions and tricks of <hi>Rachell,</hi> too hard upon my brethren. Yet what, is true is true: And God give us all grace, neither uncharitably to miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, nor perverſly or unadviſedly to give cauſe,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:21996:52"/>
to be ſuſpected, of either frowardneſſe hypocriſie or any other impiety.</p>
               <p>But as for thoſe of our brethren, which ſeperate from us in their practice and faſhion of worſhiping God; they will many (if not the moſt) of them, give (when they liſt) unto our Fathers and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors calme and ſubmiſſive langvage, at leaſt to their faces. But withall <hi>they cannot riſe, they cannot ſtand, they cannot bow, they cannot come up:</hi> They cannot ſtand nor riſe to make confeſſion of their Faith: nor to praiſe God in the congregation with hymnes and doxologies: They cannot bow at the name of <hi>Jeſus:</hi> They cannot draw neere and come up to the Communion table: But why can they not? They have the ability of their limmes (God be thanked) but more truly then <hi>Rachell</hi> may theſe men ſay <hi>the cuſtome of women is upon them.</hi> Longe ſince, the woman beganne; and ever ſince, both men and women have gotten a cuſtome, to affect and pretend more wiſdome, and knowledge then ever God laid out for them, forgetting the rule of the Apoſtle <hi>that no man thinke of himſelfe more highly then he ought to thinke: but to thinke ſoberly as God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of faith and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 22. 3. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>not to be wiſe in their owne conceits.</hi> But when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt plaine evidence of Scripture and grounds of common reaſon, men perſiſt and be overcarried againſt authority; what is this but frowardneſſe and wilfulneſſe, a very <hi>Cuſtome of women?</hi> the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of whoſe judgement, in the weakeneſſe of their ſexe, is captivated to the unrulineſſe of their
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21996:52"/>
affections, <hi>ut non perſuadeas etiamſi perſuaſeris.</hi> i. They will do what they liſt in deſpight of reaſon. And then, what is this but flat Idolatry, when their owne conceits are ſo preferred and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and God in his ordinances ſleighted.</p>
               <p>But our brethren will plead that it is not conceit or fancy, but Conſcience that withdrawes them from conforming with us, in the formes and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures uſed by us, in Gods worſhip. And then I muſt tell them, that when the things in uſe are, both by authority required, and by primitive and purer antiquity practiſed; and in their nature ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the actions which they accompany: and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where forbidden by the word of God<hi>:</hi> Their ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out in theſe things cannot be true Conſcience which is ever guided by the will of God. But fancy and ſelfe-conceit doth overbeare men; and take up that roome and power in their hearts, and that authority over their affections and practiſes which belong properly to almighty God. And ſo Conceit and Fancy is obeyed and followed, and become an Idoll, ſhutting out the Soveraignty of God, and placing it ſelfe, or rather placed by men, as a God in their hearts. <hi>For his ſervants ye are to whom ye obey.</hi> And whatſoever we ſubmit our ſelves unto contrary to the word and ordinance of God, that is by us made our God and Idoll: and we therein are become plaine Idolaters, <hi>worſhipping the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature above the Creator.</hi> And the time will come, when they ſhall plainly underſtand, that their ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of body and mind will be found out to be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:21996:53"/>
meere Idolatry: When our humble and reverend bowings ſhall be approoved for geſtures of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Devotion.</p>
               <p>And yet further, ſeeing that <hi>Superſtition,</hi> as we ſhewed before, Conſiſteth not only in overvaluing and too much doating upon the Creature, but alſo in ſtarting at the lawfull uſe of the creature: ſo as, a man thinketh himſelfe, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> defiled in his ſoule by <hi>touching, taſteing</hi> or <hi>handling</hi> of any thing which is <hi>touched, taſted or handled,</hi> without any breach of any law of God, or lawfull conſtitution of man. As for example<hi>:</hi> if a man ſhould now ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from eating Swines fleſh, in a conceit that it doth now defile or make a man a ſinner. This were plaine Superſtition. So if in time of Lent, or on any of the dayes upon the which we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Law to abſtaine from eating fleſh, a man ſhould imagine now, that it is a ſinne to eate fleſh, not ſo much in regard of the wholſome Lawes of the State and Church, which do indeede binde the conſcience. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. as in a conceit, that fleſh as it is fleſh, eaten on ſuch a day, hath a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall power to defile or make a man a ſinner: this alſo were meere Superſtition. For in both theſe caſes, a man conceiveth himſelfe defiled, and made a ſinner, by that uſe of the Creature which God ſimply forbiddeth not. And as, thus the rule holdeth in the uſe of the Creatures of God; ſo doth it alſo in the actions of men which are in themſelves indifferent. <hi>i.</hi> neither good nor bad: but as they be applyed. As for example, <hi>to kneele to bow, to</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:21996:53"/>
                  <hi>stand, to go from one place to another</hi> are things in themſelves indifferent. No where forbidden by any Law of God or man. And therefore for a man to thinke that he doth ſinne in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of any of theſe; or to abſtaine from them for feare of ſinning thereby, is plaine Superſtition. For it imputeth ſinne unto that which hath none in it.</p>
               <p>If my brethren yet alleage, that they do not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from theſe actions or geſtures, meerely as they are actions or geſtures: but as they are applied in the worſhip of God. Then I deſire to know of them, whether <hi>kneeling, bowing, ſtanding or going</hi> do of things indifferent in themſelves then become a ſinne, when I <hi>kneele to God, ſtand up to God, or go to God?</hi> And I dare boldly inough affirme it, neither need it any proofe, that there is not in our worſhip of God, any other <hi>kneeling, bowing, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or going</hi> required or uſed but unto God. Let men inſiſt where they will, and they ſhall ſoone ſee (if they be not wilfully blinde) the caſe moſt manifeſt: and that not wee, obſerving theſe things, but our brethren in their, either timerous ſtarting at them, or in their wilfull oppoſing of them, are the ſuperſtitious people: as more fully appeareth by what we have ſaid of this kind of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, before cap. 7. It is true indeed, that our brethen ſeem deſirous to ſhun Popiſh ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<hi>:</hi> But then not diſcerning between Popiſh ſuperſtition and true outward devotion, they fall upon an other worſe ſuperſtition. For true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21996:54"/>
and devotion is a vertue placed betweene two extreames: whereof, the one is <hi>ſecundum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum</hi> i. in the exceſſe or too much according to the words of <hi>Aquinas;</hi> And ſuch is much of the ſuperſtition of Popery; aſcribing too much to the creature. The other extreame <hi>ſecundum defectum.</hi> i. in the defect, or too little. And wtih this is the Anabaptiſt and Browniſt and the reſt of the ſectaries, that go in that tracke, much infected; not permitting garments or the lymbes of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or the like, to be any uſe in the worſhip of God And therefore theſe may be compared to thoſe in the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> whoſe caſe is, as if a man did fly from a Lyon and a <hi>beare met him: or went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In moral.</note> 
                  <hi>the houſe and leaned on the wall, and a ſerpent bit him:</hi> according whereto is the obſervation of St. <hi>Gregory. Quidam dum fugiunt latrones aut feras, in avia incidunt aut barathra. Sic quidam Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ita fugiunt, ut incidant in impietatem. i.</hi> Some do ſo run a way from theeves or wild beaſts, as that they fall upon Gulfes and unpaſſable places: And ſo, ſome do ſo avoyd or ſhun Superſtition as that they become impious or irreligious.</p>
               <p>If this language ſeeme too harſh to any of my brethren, I requeſt them to conſider, that theſe actions and geſtures of ours in Gods worſhip, being in themſelves indifferent, and withall applyed, not unto any Idol, or unlawfull act, but unto God; and that alſo according to antient Chriſtian pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and conſtitutions eccleſiaſticall not onely of foraigne councels, but of our owne ſtate and
<pb facs="tcp:21996:54"/>
hierachy, under ſo Chriſtian a Prince<hi>:</hi> they that refuſe herein to be conformed, ſpecially in thoſe things which be expreſſely injoyned, are therein not onely Superſtitious, but alſo guilty of one of the greateſt ſinnes, <hi>worſe than witch craft, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> which is alſo <hi>iniquity</hi> and <hi>IDOLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRIE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have we cleared our <hi>holy houſe of God, his ſervants and Service</hi> (as wee doe performe it) from all <hi>Idolatry and Superſtition.</hi> We have alſo made it manifeſt, that our accuſers themſelves are (while they are not aware) a Superſtitious people. And therefore I ſay. <hi>Brother, pull the beame of Superſtition out of thine owne eye:</hi> and then I truſt in God, <hi>thou ſhalt clearely ſee</hi> that there are no ſuch motes in our eyes, as thou diddeſt imagine. Remember that the members of thy body do, in their kinde, owe ſervice and worſhip unto God: as well as the abilities and faculties of the ſoule. Robbe not God then of his due: leaſt under a pretence of <hi>abhorring Idols, thou commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Sacrilege.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:55"/>
            <p>Imprimatur tractatus hic cui Titulus eſt <hi>(Gods holy Houſe and Service)</hi> modò in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra decem menſes proximè ſequentes, typis man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Fulhamae</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iulii ultimo.</hi> 163<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sa. Baker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:55"/>
            <head>Diverſe quotations in the Margine, ſomething out of their due places, and imperfect pointings in the pages, the Reader is requeſted to pardon. But ſuch errours as pervert the ſence of the Author, are to be mended thus.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 22 and 23. for immediatly, <hi>reade</hi> mediately. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 2 for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, <hi>r.</hi> mediately. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>b.</hi> 24. for to be, <hi>r.</hi> where was. <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 14. blot out it. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 8. and 13. for Church, <hi>r.</hi> Chriſtian. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 30. for, it is, <hi>r.</hi> is it? <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 3. for cuſtè, <hi>r.</hi> iuſtè, and <hi>l.</hi> 4. for eſſe, <hi>r.</hi> eſt. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>l</hi> 16. for becauſe Church, <hi>v.</hi> becauſe the Church, and <hi>l.</hi> 18. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 21. for were, <hi>r.</hi> where, <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>l</hi> 28. blot out, and, <hi>p.</hi> 39. in marg. for dives, <hi>r.</hi> divis. <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 18. for Church, <hi>r.</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>p.</hi> 43. <hi>l.</hi> 25. blot out not. <hi>p.</hi> 46. <hi>l.</hi> 22. for to uſe, <hi>r.</hi> to uſe it. <hi>p.</hi> 48. <hi>l.</hi> 2. for rightly, <hi>r.</hi> richly. &amp; <hi>l.</hi> 16. for which you, <hi>r.</hi> with you. &amp; <hi>l.</hi> 24. for of things, <hi>r.</hi> of the things. <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>l.</hi> 20. for and other, <hi>r.</hi> and another. <hi>p.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 10 for thyrſtie, <hi>r.</hi> thriftie. and <hi>l.</hi> 22. for ſet, <hi>r.</hi> get. <hi>p.</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 18. for the is, <hi>r.</hi> there is <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 7, 8. for charged, <hi>r.</hi> cheared. and <hi>l.</hi> 9. for that man, <hi>r.</hi> that that man. <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 31. for maketh to, <hi>r.</hi> maketh them to. <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>l.</hi> 3. for heard, <hi>r.</hi> hard. and <hi>l.</hi> 11. for vincibatur, <hi>r.</hi> vincebatur. <hi>p.</hi> 66. <hi>l.</hi> 2. for ſpirituale qua, <hi>r.</hi> ſpiritualem quam. <hi>p.</hi> 72. <hi>l.</hi> 11. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 74. <hi>l.</hi> 29. for Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus, <hi>r.</hi> Damaſus. <hi>p.</hi> 77. <hi>l.</hi> 31. blot out, in. <hi>p.</hi> 80. <hi>l.</hi> 15. for magnified, <hi>r,</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined. and <hi>l.</hi> 18, for for as, <hi>r.</hi> as for. and <hi>l.</hi> 20. for forward, <hi>r.</hi> froward. <hi>p.</hi> 86. <hi>l.</hi> 21. for oppoſitive, <hi>r.</hi> poſitive. <hi>p.</hi> 93. <hi>l.</hi> 13. for little, <hi>r.</hi> title. <hi>p.</hi> 98. <hi>l.</hi> 11. for be any, <hi>r.</hi> be of any.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:21996:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:21996:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21996:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21996:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21996:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:21996:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:21996:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:21996:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:21996:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:21996:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:21996:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:21996:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21996:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:21996:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:21996:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:21996:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:21996:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:21996:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:21996:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:21996:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:21996:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:21996:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:21996:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:21996:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:21996:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:21996:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:21996:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:21996:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:21996:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21996:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
